<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../../XML/meta/asischema.xsd"
   xml:base="schnitzler-interviews" xml:id="I009">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="s">Arthur Schnitzler: Interviews</title>
            <title level="a" ref="#32913">[Amelia Sarah Levetus]: Winner of the Grillparzer-Prize,
               28.&#8239;2.&#8239;1908</title>
            <author ref="#5119">Levetus, Amelia Sarah</author>
            <editor>
               <name>Müller, Martin Anton</name>
            </editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>ASI</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transkription und Kommentierung</resp>
               <name>Martin Anton Müller</name>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Martin Anton Müller</publisher>
            <idno type="asi" n="009"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listBibl>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="#5119">[Amelia Sarah Levetus]</author>
                     <title level="a" ref="#32913">Winner of the Grillparzer prize</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j" ref="#58324">The Jewish Chronicle</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="1908-02-28" n="1">28.&#8239;2.&#8239;1908</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="nr">2.030</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">10</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en-UK">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="approved">
         <change who="MAM" when="2017-11-17">angelegt</change>
         <change who="MAM" when="2018-02-14">Index check</change>
         <change who="KH" when="2021-10-11">Durchsicht</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="text">
      <body>
         <div type="original" xml:lang="en-US">
            <head> Winner of the <rs type="org" ref="#29677">Grillparzer Prize</rs>.</head>
            <p>The news that the <rs type="org" ref="#29677">Grillparzer prize</rs> had been awarded
               to Dr. <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs> was welcomed by all those
               who take real interest in the dramatic future of <rs type="place" ref="#41240"
                  >Austria</rs>, for though <rs type="person" ref="#11518">Grillparzer</rs> is the
               greatest of her poets and dramatists, it has rarely fallen to the lot of an Austrian
               to be the recipient of the coveted prize; which is the greatest distinction that a
               modern German dramatist can attain. Dr. <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur
                  Schnitzler</rs> is not only an <rs type="place" ref="#41240">Austrian</rs> and a
                  <rs type="place" ref="#50">Viennese</rs>, but a Jew, and one who is not ashamed of
               his Judaism. Of course, this fact has given rise to much adverse criticism on the
               part of the anti-Semitic Press, but, after all, it is not to them that men of culture
               go for information and advice, and their views may be ignored with a clear
               conscience. The <rs type="org" ref="#29677">Grillparzer prize</rs> was founded by the
                  <rs type="org" ref="#29395">Akademie der Wissenschaft</rs> during the life of <rs
                  type="person" ref="#11518">Grillparzer</rs>, who greatly appreciated the honour
               shown to him. It was his express wish that it should be awarded once in three years
               for the best German drama which had been produced during that time. It is no barren
               honour, its monetary value varying from 3,000 to 5,000 <rs type="place" ref="#41240"
                  >Austrian</rs> kronen (Dr. <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> gained
               the larger sum). Another condition was that the drama must have been produced
               successfully at a leading German theatre. Since <date>1887</date>, when the prize
               fell to <rs type="person" ref="#10772">Anzengruber</rs>, who died two years later, no
                  <rs type="place" ref="#41240">Austrian</rs> has gained the coveted honour. It is
               exactly ten years since <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>’s drama »<rs
                  type="work" ref="#29843">Der grüne Kakadu</rs>« was successfully produced at the
                  <rs type="org" ref="#36247">Imperial Hofburg</rs> (it has now gone over to the <rs
                  type="place" ref="#20">Volks Theater</rs>). This one-act drama, which deals with
               events taking place on the eve of the <rs type="place" ref="#166">French</rs>
               revolution, is exceedingly powerful in dramatic effect, language and diction. It is
               now being produced by <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="KT095-1"/>
               <rs type="person" ref="#28526">
                  <anchor type="textConst" xml:id="TT095-2"/>Baumfeld<note type="textConst"
                     xml:id="TT095-2h"><quote>Barmfeld</quote></note>
               </rs>
               <note type="commentary" xml:id="KT095-1h">Es handelte sich um die deutschsprachige
                  Inszenierung von <rs type="work" ref="#29843">Der grüne Kakadu</rs>, <rs
                     type="work" ref="#29877">Die letzten Masken</rs> und <rs type="work"
                     ref="#29869">Literatur</rs> am <rs type="place" ref="#1049">Irving Theatre</rs>
                  (Premiere am <date>29.&#8239;10.&#8239;1907</date>).</note> in <rs type="place" ref="#44053"
                  >New York</rs>.</p>
            <p>The jurors had to study and debate upon the merits of no less than ninety-four plays
               before coming to a decision. It was no ordinary jury, composed as it was of Hofrat
                  <rs type="person" ref="#12258">Minor</rs>, Professor of German Literature at the
                  <rs type="place" ref="#386">Vienna University</rs>; <rs type="person" ref="#11687"
                  >Ludwig Hevesi</rs>, the well-known art and dramatic critic; Hofrat Dr. <rs
                  type="person" ref="#11036">Max Burckhard</rs>, the former director of the <rs
                  type="org" ref="#36247">Imperial Hofburg</rs>; the present Director of the <rs
                  type="org" ref="#36247">Imperial Theatre</rs>, Dr. <rs type="person" ref="#12671"
                  >Paul Schlenther</rs>; and Geheimrat Dr. <rs type="person" ref="#12678">Erich
                  Schmidt</rs>, of <rs type="place" ref="#168">Berlin</rs>, all men known throughout
               the literary world of <rs type="place" ref="#41240">Austria</rs> and <rs type="place"
                  ref="#151">Germany</rs>, and whose fame has gone far beyond the boundaries of
               these countries. Professor Dr. <rs type="person" ref="#12903">Eduard Suess</rs>, the
               President of the <rs type="org" ref="#29395">Akademie der <anchor type="textConst"
                     xml:id="T_I009-11"/>Wissenschaften<note type="textConst" xml:id="T_I009-11h"
                        ><quote>Wissenschaft</quote></note>
               </rs>, was highly pleased with the result of the Conference, for Dr. <rs
                  type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> was chosen unanimously for his drama,
                  »<rs type="work" ref="#29903">Zwischenspiel</rs>.«</p>
            <p>Dr. <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> is but a young man, being a little
               over forty. He did not begin to write anything seriously till he was over thirty<ref
                  target="#q104" type="question"/>, but his career has been both interesting and
               successful. His <rs type="person" subtype="implied" ref="#12695">father</rs> was a
               distinguished medical man, a specialist and Professor of laryngology, whose services
               were sought far and near, and who achieved a world-wide fame. His brother, Dr. <rs
                  type="person" ref="#12698">Julius Schnitzler</rs>, is likewise distinguished as a
               surgeon. He is first surgeon of the <rs type="place" ref="#1025">Rudolfspital</rs>
               and Professor of Surgery at the <rs type="place" ref="#386">University</rs>. His only
                  <rs type="person" ref="#2461" subtype="implied">sister</rs> is married to Dr. <rs
                  type="person" ref="#2284">Marcusz Hajek</rs>, a widely-known specialist for the
               throat and ear; and lastly, <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs> is
               himself a medical man. As he says, he was brought up in the midst of medicine and it
               came to him naturally. After <anchor type="textConst" xml:id="T_I009-2"/>having
                  taken<note type="textConst" xml:id="T_I009-2h"><quote>having
                  taking</quote></note> his <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="K_I009-2"
                  />degree<note type="commentary" xml:id="K_I009-2h">Die Promotion fand am <ref
                     target="1885-05-30" type="schnitzlerDiary" subtype="date-only"/> statt.</note>,
               he <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="K_I009-1"/>went to <rs type="place" ref="#224"
                  >London</rs><note type="commentary" xml:id="K_I009-1h">von <ref
                     target="1888-05-21" type="schnitzlerDiary" subtype="date-only"/> bis zum <ref
                     target="1888-08-25" type="schnitzlerDiary" subtype="date-only"/></note>, where
               he spent several months walking the hospitals and studying their systems. On his
               return to <rs type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs>, he set up as a practitioner, won
               acknowledgment and was in the way of becoming a specialist like his <rs type="person"
                  subtype="implied" ref="#12695">father</rs>. <ref target="#q161" type="question"
               />Fortunately, his bent towards literature and the drama especially, were greater
               than his love for medicine, and he became a writer. His preparation bad been a wide
               one; not only had he travelled and seen the great cities of the Continent, but he bad
               also been a voracious reader. From the first he proved himself a writer of no mean
               talent, and his novels and dramas attained immediate popularity. One of his earliest
               stories, »<rs type="work" ref="#29853">Leutenant Gustl</rs>,« brought him into
               conflict with the military authorities and cost him his rank as Lieutenant in the
               Reserve. It is twelve years since his first drama, »<anchor type="textConst"
                  xml:id="TT095-1"/>
               <rs type="work" ref="#29917">Liebelei</rs>
               <note type="textConst" xml:id="TT095-1h"><quote>Lieberlei</quote></note>,« was
               produced at the <rs type="org" ref="#36247">Imperial Hofburg Theater</rs>. This at
               once gained him fame, and, with few exceptions, all his dramas have been successfully
               produced on this stage. For some reason or other, »<rs type="work" ref="#29857">Der
                  Schleier der Beatrice</rs>« was censored in <rs type="place" ref="#50"
                  >Vienna</rs>, but it was, nevertheless, produced. <rs type="person" ref="#2121"
                  >Schnitzler</rs> has even met with more appreciation in <rs type="place"
                  ref="#168">Berlin</rs> than in <rs type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs>, but »a man
               is never a prophet in his own country,« and <rs type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs> is
                  <rs type="place" ref="#41240">Austria</rs>. He possesses a fine and cultivated
               intellect, keen, perceptive faculties, natural warmth, and poetic fire and
               expression. He is <rs type="place" ref="#50">Viennese</rs> to the core, with all that
               charm and grace for which inhabitants of the Austrian capital are celebrated. He is
               essentially a modern dramatist; what he says is trenchant and to the point, though he
               is never coarse. The prize drama, »<rs type="work" ref="#29903">Zwischenspiel</rs>,«
               deals with the modern marriage question, and the relation of the wife to her husband
               and to her lover. He treats the question with real earnestness.</p>
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>’s diction is flowing and sonorous, his
               language easy and musical. Needless to say, Dr. <rs type="person" ref="#2121"
                  >Schnitzler</rs> takes a warm interest in all questions of the day and all that
               concerns Judaism. <ref target="#q088" type="question"/>He hopes for a solution of the
               anti-Semitic question, and treats of it in his serial romance »<rs type="work"
                  ref="#29923">
                  <hi rend="italics">Der Weg ins freie</hi>
               </rs>,« which is now appearing in <rs type="work" ref="#36156">
                  <hi rend="italics">
                     <anchor type="textConst" xml:id="T_I009-1"/>Die Neue<note type="textConst"
                        xml:id="T_I009-1h"><quote>Der Neue</quote></note> Rundschau</hi>
               </rs>, but it is impossible to criticise his views till the story is completed. It
               will be published in book form in <date>August</date>. <ref target="#q167"
                  type="question"/>He is also interested in the Zionist movement, though he takes no
               active part in it. </p>
            <p>Add to all that has been said, that he is about middle stature, fair and with
               charming manners and withal a modest man, and you have a complete picture of Dr. <rs
                  type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biographical">
            <div1>
               <ref type="schnitzlerDiary" target="1908-01-28"/>
               <quote>Nm. Miss <rs type="person" ref="#5119">Levetus</rs> (<rs type="org"
                     ref="#29392">Jewish Chronicle</rs>) interviewte mich hauptsächlich über den
                  Antisemitismus.–</quote>
            </div1>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
