<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../meta/asischema.xsd"
   xml:base="schnitzler-interviews" xml:id="I022">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="s">Arthur Schnitzler: Interviews</title>
            <title level="a" ref="#32969">Herman Bernstein: Nations Must Check the Spread of Hate
               Declares Noted Austrian, 17.&#8239;9.&#8239;1922</title>
            <author ref="#5160">Bernstein, Herman</author>
            <editor>
               <name>Müller, Martin Anton</name>
            </editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>ASI</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transkription und Kommentierung</resp>
               <name>Martin Anton Müller</name>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Martin Anton Müller</publisher>
            <idno type="asi" n="022"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listBibl>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="#5160">Bernstein, Herman</author>
                     <title level="a" ref="#32969">Nations Must Check the Spread of Hate Declares
                        Noted Austrian</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j" ref="#58339">New York American</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="1922-09-17" n="1">17. 9. 1922</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="nr">14.305</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="sec">March of Events</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">6</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="#5160">Bernstein, Herman</author>
                     <title level="a">What Is Becoming of Europe. From an Interview With Arthur
                        Schnitzler</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j">Jewish Daily News</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="1922-09-21" n="1">21. 9. 1922</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="vol">38</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="nr">222</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">[12]</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="#5160">Bernstein, Herman</author>
                     <title level="a" ref="#32969">Arthur Schnitzler</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="m">Celebrities of our Time. Interviews</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Joseph Lawren</publisher>
                        <date when="1924">1924</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">318–325</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <!-- https://archive.org/stream/celebritiesofour000452mbp#page/n343/mode/2up -->
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="#5160">Bernstein, Herman</author>
                     <title level="a">What is becoming of Europe?</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j">The Jewish Exponent</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="1925-01-16" n="1">16. 1. 1925</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="vol">75</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="nr">17</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">8</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en-US">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="approved">
         <change who="MAM" when="2018-01-24">angelegt</change>
         <change who="MAM" when="2018-02-14">Index check</change>
         <change who="KH" when="2021-10-20">Durchsicht</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="text">
      <body>
         <div type="original" xml:lang="en-US">
            <head>Nations Must Check the Spread of Hate</head>
            <head type="sub">Declares Noted <rs type="place" ref="#41240">Austrian</rs>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <rs type="person" ref="#2121">
                  <anchor type="textConst" xml:id="T_I022-1"/>Schnitzler<note type="textConst"
                     xml:id="T_I022-1h"><quote>Schnitzer</quote></note>
               </rs>, Leader of <rs type="place" ref="#50">Viennese</rs> Dramatists</head>
            <head type="sub">»What Is Becoming of <rs type="place" ref="#468">Europe</rs>?« Asks
               Master Mind – »We See More Hate Than Before the War« – The Terror of Old Battles and
               Slaughter is Lost in the Vistas of Time – World has Grown Careless of Human
               Life.</head>
            <head type="sub">By Herman Bernstein</head>
            <p>
               <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="KT108-1"/>What<note type="commentary"
                  xml:id="KT108-1h">Bevor es bei beiden mit »<quote>
                     <foreign xml:lang="en-US">›What is becoming of <rs type="place" ref="#468"
                           >Europe</rs>?‹</foreign></quote>« losgeht, wiederholt die Zeitschriftenfassung die ersten beiden Absätze
                  des Interviews aus dem Jahr <date>1916</date> (<ref target="#I019" type="pointer"
                  />) und fügt einen Satz hinzu; die Buchausgabe bringt stattdessen folgende
                  Einleitung: »<quote>
                     <foreign xml:lang="en-US">I met <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur
                           Schnitzler</rs> in his study in <rs type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs>. A
                        fine copy of <rs type="work" ref="#31935">Mona Lisa</rs> was conspicuous
                        among the numerous portraits on the walls, and on his desk stood a <rs
                           type="work" ref="#33013" subtype="implied">statuette</rs> of <rs
                           type="person" ref="#11461">Goethe</rs>. The brilliant <rs type="place"
                           ref="#50">Viennese</rs> dramatist and novelist, whose sixtieth birthday
                        was recently celebrated by his friends and admirers, is youthful despite the
                        gray in his hair and beard, and his kindly smile is as full of charm as
                        ever. During the past few months many eulogies by the foremost dramatists,
                        novelists and critics appeared in various <rs type="place" ref="#468"
                           >European</rs> periodicals and newspapers. / <rs type="person"
                           ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> is beloved by all who know him. All agree
                        that his artistic works are marked with a peculiar charm and are of lasting
                        value. He has portrayed men and women as they really are – with their dreams
                        and their passions, their foibles and their follies. / <rs type="person"
                           ref="#11617">Gerhardt Hauptmann</rs>, summing up the achievements of <rs
                           type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> thus far, <rs type="work"
                           ref="#31455" subtype="implied">writes</rs> that to have an appreciation
                        of <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> is to have an appreciation
                        of art and culture. <rs type="person" ref="#10815">Hermann Bahr</rs>
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <rs type="work" ref="#31455" subtype="implied">predicts</rs> that <rs
                           type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> will fare better than other
                        writers a hundred years hence, for when future generations will want to
                        study the traits, the modes of life and thought during the years of <rs
                           type="place" ref="#41240">Austria</rs>’s sunset, they will have to go
                        back to <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> who mirrored that
                        sunset most clearly, who reproduced as no one else the last charm of<pb/>
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <rs type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs> in the shadows, who was the doctor at
                        her death bed, who loved her more deeply than anyone else, who was the last
                        poet of her agony. / <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> spoke
                        with deep emotion of <rs type="place" ref="#41240">Austria</rs>’s pathetic
                        plight, of the beauty and grandeur of her landscapes and of her still
                        undeveloped opportunities, of the curse of too much politics in <rs
                           type="place" ref="#41240">Austria</rs>, and for that matter in the whole
                        of <rs type="place" ref="#468">Europe</rs>, and then he pointed to the
                        growth of prejudice and hate after the war.</foreign></quote>«. Von gesondertem Interesse sind die beiden erwähnten Kunstwerke. <rs
                     type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> dürfte die Kopie der <rs type="work"
                     ref="#31935">Mona Lisa</rs> in Originalgröße noch vor der Popularisierung des
                  Kunstwerks durch einen spektakulären Diebstahl aus dem <rs type="org" ref="#63428"
                     >Louvre</rs><space unit="chars" quantity="1"/><date>1911</date> erworben haben.
                  Sie ist noch auf den letzten Fotos seines Arbeitszimmers zu erkennen. (<bibl>Vgl.
                        <title level="m">A.&#8239;S. und die bildende Kunst</title> 110–111</bibl>.)
                  Die Keramikstatue von Powolny ist auch in einem anderen Interview erwähnt, <ref
                     type="pointer" target="#I061_L_schlafrockii"/>. Die Texte <rs type="person"
                     ref="#11617">Hauptmanns</rs> und <rs type="person" ref="#10815">Bahrs</rs>, auf
                  die Bezug genommen werden, erschienen beide im <rs type="person" ref="#2121"
                     >Schnitzler</rs> gewidmeten Heft der <rs type="work" ref="#36156">Neuen
                     Rundschau</rs> vom <date>Mai 1922</date>.</note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <rs type="person" ref="#11798">Henryk Ibsen</rs> was to the <rs type="place"
                  ref="#64465">Norwegian</rs> drama, <rs type="person" ref="#12877">August
                  Strindberg</rs> to the <rs type="place" ref="#44335">Swedish</rs>, <rs
                  type="person" ref="#3603">Anton Chekhov</rs> to the <rs type="place" ref="#34438"
                  >Russian</rs>, what <rs type="person" ref="#11617">Gerhardt Hauptmann</rs> is to
               the <rs type="place" ref="#151">German</rs> drama, <rs type="person" ref="#2381"
                  >Bernard Shaw</rs> to the <rs type="place" ref="#254">English</rs> and <rs
                  type="person" ref="#12156">Maurice Maeterlinck</rs> to the <rs type="place"
                  ref="#166">French</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs> is to
               the Austrian drama to-day. Keen and penetrating, brilliant and subtle, a master of
               irony and satire, yet sincere and full of optimism, this master builder of the modern
                  <rs type="place" ref="#41240">Austrian</rs> drama, this <rs type="place" ref="#50"
                  >Viennese</rs> man of letters has impressed himself profoundly upon the literature
               of <rs type="place" ref="#41240">Austria</rs> in the face of innumerable
               difficulties.</p>
            <p>By the sheer force of his art, as it manifested itself in his works, in masterpiece
               after masterpiece, Dr. <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs>, a Jew,
               has won distinction in <rs type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs>, the very hotbed of
               anti-semitism. He has surmounted many obstacles, combating prejudice calmly, yet with
               firm determination.</p>
            <p>The following interview was had in the study of this brilliant writer in <rs
                  type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs>:</p>
            <p>»What is becoming of <rs type="place" ref="#468">Europe</rs>?« said <rs type="person"
                  ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>. »The hate which has been intensified by the war is
               growing and spreading, and the most dreadful feature of it all is that people are
               talking of now wars in the near future.</p>
            <p>
               <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="KT108-2"/>»It<note type="commentary"
                  xml:id="KT108-2h">In der Buchausgabe beginnt der Absatz mit: »<quote>
                     <foreign xml:lang="en-US">›On <date>August 1, 1914</date>, – on the day of the
                        declaration of war – I wrote a letter to my <rs type="person" ref="#12698"
                           subtype="implied">brother</rs> of which I should have been ashamed a
                        little later. I gave him my reasons why it was impossible that such a world
                        war could take place. It was a foolish letter in view of the events that
                        followed so rapidly, and that involved practically the whole world in the
                        war. But only now – after several years of so-called peace, we see clearly
                        that the war was really impossible.</foreign></quote>«</note> was the most brutal of all wars, it destroyed more values than
                  <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="K_I022-45"/>any previous war<note
                  type="commentary" xml:id="K_I022-45h">In der Buchausgabe ist der Satz erweitert
                  um: »<quote>and it has left the world in a much worse condition than it was before
                     the war.</quote>«</note>. We see chaos, poverty, ruination everywhere in <rs
                  type="place" ref="#468">Europe</rs>. And we see more hate than before the war.</p>
            <head type="sub">Spread of Hate</head>
            <p>»To check this spread of hate in various countries, it seems to me that it is urgent
               for intellectual leaders everywhere to create good will and a better understanding
               among the nations. A great campaign of education is essential in that direction.</p>
            <p>»We have seen that Socialism has failed to meet the problems of war and peace
               effectively and has not exerted much of an influence either in the war or in the
               making of peace.</p>
            <p>»We must realise, first of all, that man is the worst of all animals – the most cruel
               of them all. The difference between the human being and other animals is that the
               human being possesses such traits as joy at <anchor type="textConst"
                  xml:id="T_I022-11"/>another’s<note type="textConst" xml:id="T_I022-11h"
                     ><quote>anoher’s</quote></note> misfortune. Animals have no such terrible
               traits.</p>
            <p>»We must also realise that while the human mind may be improved by education the
               human soul cannot be improved – for it cannot be changed. We may, therefore, hope
               that human beings will some day become wiser, but they cannot become better. Human
               beings are born egotists. They do not love one another unselfishly – they hate one
               another.</p>
            <p>»All we may hope for is that the intellectual leaders may succeed in showing the
               people that they must stop wars because it would be best for them to have no wars –
               because they would benefit more from peace than from war.</p>
            <head type="sub">Practical Pacificism </head>
            <p>»Pacifism should not be sentimental. That is useless. Pacifists should not say that
               it is wrong to kill; that it is unethical to destroy human life; that it is immoral
               to commit such a crime; that other people suffer from such destruction, and that war
               is terrible on that account.</p>
            <p>»Everybody knows that war is terrible; that it leaves dead and maimed in its wake;
               that it destroys property, and retards what is known as civilization. But such
               methods of reasoning, such arguments are of no avail. Human beings are not impressed
               by them. Human beings do not change their nature on that account.</p>
            <p>»Instead of sentimental pacifism it is essential to convince them by education that
               peace would benefit them and save them – that in a roundabout way they themselves or
               their children may be the victims of war – the wounded, the mutilated, the dead.</p>
            <head type="sub">The Quality of Love</head>
            <p>»It is of very little value to preach love and the brotherhood of man, for it does
               not help. There are some people who believe that it is enough for them to preach or
               to listen to sermons on loving one’s neighbor as themselves – and that by this they
               have already discharged all their duties to their fellow-men.</p>
            <p>»The quality of unselfish love is not inherent in human beings – and it is useless to
               demand of human beings to change that which cannot be changed. Besides, it is not
               necessary at all. I do not want people to love me. I do not want their kisses. I
               don’t think it necessary that there should be too much love among the nations.</p>
            <p>»The important thing is that people should realize that they must not wrong one
               another – that they must not hurt or injure one another. The important thing is that
               people should have the opportunity to work, undisturbed, in peace; that they should
               not interfere with others; that they should not destroy others; that they should not
               rob others. They must learn to realise that war will affect them directly in some way
               or other just as they believe war would affect their enemy, their neighbor.</p>
            <head type="sub">Rejoicing in Death</head>
            <p>»Yesterday, while my <rs type="person" ref="#2238" subtype="implied">daughter</rs>
               was packing to go to the country, we found a batch of old newspapers published during
               the war. I looked at the headlines. ›The Battle of – .‹<space unit="chars"
                  quantity="1"/>›We Captured 50,000 men. Tens of Thousands Slain.‹ And the
               jubilation over each victory! I remember how our people rejoiced when they heard that
               thousands of <rs type="place" ref="#34438">Russians</rs> were drowned in swamps.</p>
            <p>»I was filled with terror as I recalled all this. Of course, the other side did
               exactly the same. They too, rejoiced when hundreds of thousands of our people were
               slaughtered. And I recalled with horror the indifference with which people afterwards
               read about those battles.</p>
            <p>»When, for instance, they read that fifty thousand men had been slain, and on the
               following morning the revised figures showed that instead of fifty thousand there
               really were sixty thousand casualties, did that difference disturb the people’s
               sleep, or did it affect their appetites? Not in the least. They went on eating,
               drinking and smoking their cigars.</p>
            <p>»In fact, the men at the front hated the ›enemy‹ less than the people in the rear –
               we know that at the front the men often fraternized with the ›enemy,‹ while the
               people in the rear hated the ›enemy‹ intensely – and this hate is continuing. And in
               certain places it is even encouraged deliberately – fanned and spread <anchor
                  type="commentary" xml:id="KT108-3"/>artificially.<note type="commentary"
                  xml:id="KT108-3h">In der Buchausgabe folgt ein weiterer Absatz: »<quote>
                     <foreign xml:lang="en-US">›If we read about some distant island sinking into
                        the ocean with a population of a half a million human beings we would
                        actually be affected by such news much less than by the natural death of
                        someone on our block. If a fire breaks out in our neighbor’s house, we are
                        upset and worried to the extent that we fear lest the fire should spread to
                        our own house. If a fire breaks out somewhere in our city, we are worried
                        because it may destroy the house of one of our relatives or friends. If we
                        hear of a fire in a distant part of our city where we have no relatives or
                        friends, we go on smoking our cigars undisturbed.</foreign></quote>«</note>
            </p>
            <head type="sub">Careless of Life</head>
            <p>»I recall a simple, quite unimportant incident, but it is so characteristic that I
               will tell it to you. Some years ago my <rs type="person" subtype="implied"
                  ref="#2173">wife</rs> had scarlet fever. We had a <anchor type="commentary"
                  xml:id="K_implied_27740"/>
               <rs type="person" subtype="implied" ref="#27740">nurse</rs>
               <note type="commentary" xml:id="K_implied_27740h">nicht identifiziert. Die Erkrankung
                  bestand im <date>Dezember 1907</date>.</note> who attended her. The <rs
                  type="person" ref="#27740" subtype="implied">nurse</rs> was very correct, devoted,
               efficient and intelligent.</p>
            <p>»When my <rs type="person" ref="#2173" subtype="implied">wife</rs> recovered and the
                  <rs type="person" ref="#27740" subtype="implied">nurse</rs> was to leave, she had
               to wait about a quarter of an hour for an ambulance which was to fumigate her clothes
               in order that she may not infect other people.</p>
            <p>»When I went out of the house a few minutes later, I noticed to my great amazement
               that the <rs type="person" ref="#27740" subtype="implied">nurse</rs> entered a
               crowded street car, without having waited for the ambulance. She had no patience to
               wait fifteen minutes, and she went home by car without having taken the necessary
               precaution. She probably infected a number of people in that car with scarlet
               fever.</p>
            <p>»Here was a <rs type="person" ref="#27740" subtype="implied">nurse</rs> who knew well
               the dangers of such contagion. She was intelligent and it was her profession to look
               after patients, and be careful. But that did not matter to her. She went into the
               crowded street car because the passengers were just ordinary people whom she did not
               know. They were strangers to her, and she did not care.</p>
            <p>»But if, for instance, <rs type="person" ref="#27740" subtype="implied">she</rs> were
               to learn that someone was infected in that car by her, and that such person carried
               the disease to a child who happened to be a schoolmate of her own child, and in that
               way infected her own child – and her own child died as a result, of her recklessness
               and neglect, then she would think and act differently in the future.</p>
            <head type="sub">Benefits of Peace</head>
            <p>»Of course, if such a thing happened, people would say that it was an unusual case, a
               rare coincidence. But if people were to figure things out logically they would find
               that the wrong they do to others in some way or other necessarily reacts on
               themselves – they would understand that, and would stop wronging others. As I have
               said before, human beings may become wiser, but they will never grow better.</p>
            <p>»It is therefore the important task of intellectual leaders everywhere to organise
               themselves and start a campaign to enlighten the people that peace is in their own
               interests – that war will ruin them, while peace will <anchor type="commentary"
                  xml:id="KT108-4"/>benefit them.«<note type="commentary" xml:id="KT108-4h">Die
                  Buchausgabe hat hier vier weitere Absätze: »<quote>
                     <p>
                        <foreign xml:lang="en-US">›Why don’t you develop this idea more elaborately
                           in an article?‹ I suggested.</foreign>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <foreign xml:lang="en-US">
                           <pb/>›I can’t write articles,‹ replied Dr. <rs type="person" ref="#2121"
                              >Schnitzler</rs>. ›I have often been asked to write articles for the
                              <rs type="org" ref="#29351">
                              <hi rend="italics">Neue Freie Presse</hi>
                           </rs>. I have often discussed certain subjects with the publisher and
                           editor of that newspaper, and he often said to me: ›Let me have an
                           article on this subject. This is just what I need.‹ I have always
                           declined to write articles. I often wonder why journalists and publicists
                           underestimate their own ability to write articles and believe that
                           novelists or dramatists must necessarily know how to write
                           articles.‹</foreign>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <foreign xml:lang="en-US">›But in this instance you have advanced the best
                           reasons why you should write something on this theme, particularly when
                           you pointed out that the intellectual leaders should at this juncture do
                           the utmost to make people realize the effects of war and peace on
                           themselves,‹ I said.</foreign>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <foreign xml:lang="en-US">›I am afraid you would be disappointed if I wrote
                           an article on this subject. I really could not do it,‹ he
                           replied.</foreign>
                     </p></quote>«</note>
            </p>
            <p>Our conversation turned to his dramatic works. Suddenly he asked:</p>
            <p>»How would you account for the fact that <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="K_I022-1"
               />some of my plays<note type="commentary" xml:id="K_I022-1h">das trifft nur auf <rs
                     type="work" ref="#29855">Reigen</rs> zu</note> which were written twenty or
               twenty-five years ago are being produced only now? They seem to attract more
               attention now than when I wrote them.«</p>
            <p>»Your works were at least a quarter of a century ahead of their time,« I answered,
               »Only now people are beginning to understand and appreciate them fully.«</p>
            <p>When I mentioned »<rs type="work" ref="#29855">Reigen</rs>,« his sex play which
               created a sensation last year in <rs type="place" ref="#168">Berlin</rs> and <rs
                  type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs> and which was at first suppressed by the German
               censor, <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> remarked modestly:</p>
            <p>»›<rs type="work" ref="#29855">Reigen</rs>‹ is an ordinary play. The dialogues were
               written more than twenty-five years-ago. When this play of mine will long have been
               forgotten, the record of the <rs type="place" ref="#168">Berlin</rs> trial connected
               with ›<rs type="work" ref="#29855">Reigen</rs>‹ will live. The <anchor
                  type="commentary" xml:id="KT108-5"/>stenographic report<note type="commentary"
                  xml:id="KT108-5h"><ref type="pointer" target="#I113_L_reigenprozess"/></note> of
               the testimony at that trial is the most amazing satire of our time. The four or five
               figures that revealed themselves in that extraordinary document are types of
               hypocrisy that the greatest of satirists could hardly have invented or improved
               upon.«</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biographical">
            <div1>
               <ref type="schnitzlerDiary" target="1922-07-12"/>
               <quote>Vm. Hr. <rs type="person" ref="#5160">Hermann Bernstein</rs> (<rs type="place"
                     ref="#175">Amerika</rs>, der Journalist, der mich schon vor 2&#160;J.
                  interviewt hat). Redete drei Stunden, allgemeines und spec. politisches – er
                  wollte durchaus daß ich ihm einen Artikel schreibe – was ich ablehnte. Dann
                  literarisch geschäftliches; Ratschlag mich an die <rs type="org" ref="#29436"
                     >League of auth<supplied>ors</supplied>. Am<supplied>erica</supplied>.</rs>
                  etc. zu wenden.–</quote>
            </div1>
            <div1>
               <bibl>Schnitzler an <rs type="person" ref="#5160">Bernstein</rs>,
                     <date>18.&#8239;10.&#8239;1922</date>
               </bibl>
               <quote>Vor allem danke ich Ihnen vielmals für die freundliche Uebersendung Ihres
                  Interviews, das ich vorzüglich finde. Präzis und konzis zugleich.</quote>
            </div1>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
