<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../meta/asischema.xsd"
   xml:base="schnitzler-interviews" xml:id="I028">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="s">Arthur Schnitzler: »Das Zeitlose ist von kürzester Dauer.« Interviews, Meinungen, Proteste (1891–1931)</title>
            <title level="a" ref="#32995">J.&#8239;L.&#8239;Benvenisti: Arthur Schnitzler.&#8239;A
               Snap Shot, 29.&#8239;2.&#8239;1924</title>
            <author ref="#14026">Benvenisti, James Lincoln</author>
            <editor>
               <name>Müller, Martin Anton</name>
            </editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>ASI</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transkription und Kommentierung</resp>
               <name>Martin Anton Müller</name>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Martin Anton Müller</publisher>
            <idno type="asi" n="028"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listWit>
               <witness n="1">
                  <msDesc>
                     <msIdentifier>
                        <country>UK</country>
                        <settlement>University of Exeter</settlement>
                        <repository>The Schnitzler Press-Cuttings Archive</repository>
                        <idno>Box 38/4</idno>
                     </msIdentifier>
                     <physDesc>
                        <p>Typoskript, 7 Seiten, teilweise maschinell, teilweise handschriftlich
                           paginiert. Handschriftliche Korrekturen und Ergänzungen, vor allem der
                           letzten Zeilen, mutmaßlich von Benvenisti. Auf der ersten Seite im
                           rechten oberen Eck von Schnitzlers Hand »<quote>Benvenisti</quote>«. Die
                           Wiedergabe verzichtet auf die Differenzierung maschineller Korrekturen
                           und behebt auch stillschweigend offensichtliche Tippfehler im Einklang
                           mit dem Erstdruck.</p>
                     </physDesc>
                  </msDesc>
               </witness>
            </listWit>
            <listBibl>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="#14026">Benvenisti, J. L.</author>
                     <title level="a" ref="#32995">Arthur Schnitzler Foretells Jewish Renaissance.
                        An Exclusive Interview With the Eminent Littérateur</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j" ref="#56601">The American Hebrew</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="1924-02-29" n="1">29. 2. 1924</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">460, 474</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="#14026">Benvenisti, J. L.</author>
                     <title level="a" ref="#32995">Arthur Schnitzler Foretells Jewish Renaissance.
                        An Interview with the Eminent Litterateur</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j">The Canadian Jewish Chronicle</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="1924-03-21" n="1">21. 3. 1924</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="jg">10</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="nr">37</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">13</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Riedmann, Bettina</author>
                     <title level="m">Ich bin Jude, Österreicher, Deutscher. Judentum in Arthur
                        Schnitzlers Tagebüchern und Briefen</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="2002" n="1">2002</date>
                        <pubPlace>Tübingen</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Max Niemeyer</publisher>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">396–399</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
                  <series>
                     <title level="s">Conditio Judaica. Studien und Quellen zur deutsch-jüdischen
                        Literatur- und Kulturgeschichte</title>
                     <biblScope unit="nr">36</biblScope>
                  </series>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="#2121">Schnitzler, Arthur</author>
                     <title level="a">Arthur Schnitzler sagt jüdische Wiedergeburt voraus</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="m">Das Rote Wien. Schlüsseltexte der Zweiten Wiener Moderne 1919–1934</title>
                     <editor>Hg. Rob McFarland, Georg Spitaler, Ingo Zechner</editor>
                     <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Berlin, Boston</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>deGruyter</publisher>
                        <date when="2020">2020</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">253–255</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en-US">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="approved">
         <change who="MAM" when="2017-11-17">angelegt</change>
         <change who="MAM" when="2018-02-14">Index check</change>
         <change who="KH" when="2021-10-25">Durchsicht</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="text">
      <body>
         <div type="original" xml:lang="en-US">
            <head>Arthur Schnitzler: A Snap Shot.</head>
            <p>
               <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="TT114-1"/>He<note type="commentary"
                  xml:id="TT114-1h">Das gedruckte Interview hat zusätzlich einen Kasten mit
                  folgenden einleitenden Worten: »<quote>
                     <rs type="person" ref="#2121">
                        <hi rend="capitals">Arthur Schnitzler</hi>
                     </rs>, perhaps best known to English readers through his ›<rs type="work"
                        ref="#29935">Anatol</rs>‹ cycle, ›<rs type="work" ref="#29923">The Road to
                        the Open</rs>,‹ ›<rs type="work" ref="#42883">Casanova’s Homecoming</rs>‹
                     and <supplied>›</supplied>
                     <rs type="work" ref="#30201">Dr. Graesler</rs>,‹ stands in the forefront, not
                     only of Jewish creative artists, but of the creative artists of the world as
                     well. His faith, therefore, in the coming of a great Jewish artistic
                     renaissance is a faith which must give pride and hope to every member of the
                     Jewish community. <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs> here
                     sets forth his views on Zionism, anti-Semitism and kindred subjects.</quote>«
                  und ein Porträt mit der Bildunterschrift: »<quote>
                     <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs> / Playwright, Poet,
                     Philosopher / Physician and Psychologist</quote>«</note> strikes one as a man
               who needs all the force of his personality to keep his overwhelming brains quiet.
               That is the dominant impression I had <add place="above">of <rs type="person"
                     ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs>
               </add> after twenty minutes of the most inspiring talk I have enjoyed with any man
               for <del rend="strikethrough">many</del> months.</p>
            <p>In a way this impression comes as a surprise. For there are in <rs type="person"
                  ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>’s writing certain qualities of suavity which like the
               outward reserve of a well mannered person, are only the outcome of good artistic
               breeding, but which to superficial people belie the real temperament both of the
               artist and the man. Even a sympathetic and imaginative study of <rs type="person"
                  ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>’s works will not always correct the error, and that is
               why I, as doubtless many others have done before me, came to him, expecting to find a
               personality cold, polished and courteous, a man of urbane scepticism, and gentle
               disillusionments, a temperamental agnostic, chastened of both anger and
               enthusiasm.</p>
            <p>Of course all these things are precisely, what Schnitzler is not. The first thing
               that strikes one about him is <subst>
                  <del rend="strikethrough">the</del>
                  <add place="inline">a</add>
               </subst> most lov<subst>
                  <del rend="strikethrough">
                     <gap unit="chars" reason="illegible" quantity="2"/>
                  </del>
                  <add place="inline">able</add>
               </subst> warmth and impetuousnes<add place="inline">s</add>. He is both mentally and
               physically a young man, despite his years. His eye is clear, his complexion rosy, and
               his grey hair and beard are shot with streaks of blond. In his mental attitude <rs
                  type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> is equally youthful. Whatever subject he
               touches, he is immediately on fire. His whole heart is in his talk, and he spends
               himself in it as recklessly as a boy of eighteen.<pb/>
            </p>
            <p>I found <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> in his little house in the
               suburbs of <rs type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs>, in itself no mean achievement
               (finding him, I <anchor type="textConst" xml:id="T_I028-1"/>mean)<note
                  type="textConst" xml:id="T_I028-1h"><quote>mean</quote></note>
               <unclear>,</unclear> for <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> is one of the
               most sought after people in <rs type="place" ref="#468">Europe</rs> and has more or
               less to barricade himself against intruders. <rs type="person" ref="#2121"
                  >Schnitzler</rs> had broken off some dictation to come down to me, and had so to
               speak to rub his eyes a little before he could launch out on the new topic. Also he
               seemed at first disinclined to grant the interview.</p>
            <p>»I never give interviews,« he said. »All I have to say on the Jewish question is in
               my book ›<rs type="work" ref="#29923">Der Weg in’s Freie</rs>‹ I recommend – – –«</p>
            <p>»Herr Doctor,« I said, »I have not read <rs type="work" ref="#29923">Der Weg in’s
                  Freie</rs> once but three times and it is to discuss that book I have come to
               you.« An extraordinarily sweet smile broke out over Schnitzler’s face.</p>
            <p>»You are very flattering,« he said, and motioned me to a seat. And quite suddenly we
               were talking together<del rend="strikethrough"> at 90 miles an hour</del>.</p>
            <p>Talking to <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> is a delightful business.
               The same sense of grace and form that is so perceptible in his books, is evident in
               his talk and bearing, despite his vehemence and ready enthusiasm. He has among other
               things a perfect genius for letting himself be interrupted. If he sees you have
               something to say he waves you off so to speak for a couple of sentences, and then
               gives you a fraction of a second to leap into the talk. It is like an obliging bus
               driver slowing down between the official stopping places.<pb/>
            </p>
            <p>As one speaks to him, <subst>
                  <del rend="strikethrough">one</del>
                  <add place="above">and</add>
               </subst> becomes conscious of this terrific depth and intensity of feeling of the
               continous mental rush going on with<add place="inline">in</add> the man<add
                  place="inline">,</add> one forms some conception of the degree of unrelenting
               discipline it must cost <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> to have what he
               is namely one of the most polished and urbane writers in contemporary <rs
                  type="place" ref="#468">Europe</rs>. How easily that quick sensitivity, that
               overready response of the heart might have swamped his judgment and dimmed his taste!
               If <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> had not been <rs type="person"
                  ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>, he would one feels (not without a silent thanksgiving
               to Heaven for a calamity so nearly averted<add place="inline">)</add>, have made one
               of those prolific emotional writers, who despite the presence of real talent never
               rise higher than the second rank in in the artistic hierarchy. <anchor
                  type="commentary" xml:id="KT114-2"/>I remember thinking at the time that God hat
               originally intended <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> for a sort of <rs
                  type="person" ref="#5182">Upton Sinclair</rs>, and then at the last minute changed
               his mind.<note type="commentary" xml:id="KT114-2h">Dieser Satz durch eine Linie vom
                  Anfang des übernächsten Absatzes hierher bewegt.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is that there are two <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>s. There
               is the emotional Schnitzler with the irresistible creative urge in him, and there is
               his mentor warder and familiar spirit, the critical <rs type="person" ref="#2121"
                  >Schnitzler</rs>, and it is by a collaboration of the two separate individuals
               that <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>’s works come into being. This
               critical <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>, I don’t mind telling you, is
               the devil of a fellow. He is persistent wakeful and utterly unrelenting. Even in his
               own domain, having no other object for his <add place="inline">fury</add>, he turns
               and lacerates himself.</p>
            <p>»When I attempt any sort of critical or reflective writing,« said <rs type="person"
                  ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>, »I am half strangled by my own parentheses.«</p>
            <p>In other words <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> is one of those not
               altogether enviable<pb/>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <anchor type="textConst" xml:id="T_I028-2"/>individuals whose<note type="textConst"
                  xml:id="T_I028-2h"><quote>whose</quote></note> judgments and critical faculty
               never have a holiday. It is a heavy price to pay, but in <rs type="person"
                  ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>’s case the game is <anchor type="textConst"
                  xml:id="T_I028-12"/>worth the candle<note type="textConst" xml:id="T_I028-12h"
                     ><quote>worth candle</quote></note>.</p>
            <p>That <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> should have had plenty to say on
               the Jewish question, was only to be expected. He has written about it enough. »<rs
                  type="work" ref="#30203">Professor Bernhardi</rs>« touches it. The immortal
               ineffable »<anchor type="commentary" xml:id="K_I028-43"/><rs type="work" ref="#29853">
                  <anchor type="textConst"
                     xml:id="T_I028-11"/>Lieutenant<note type="textConst" xml:id="T_I028-11h"
                        ><quote>Lietnant</quote></note> Gustl</rs>« is full of it<note
                  type="commentary" xml:id="K_I028-43h">Zwar äußert die Titelfigur einiges
                  Antisemitisches, doch scheint die Behauptung, es ginge darin um die »jüdische
                  Frage« vor allem die Unkenntnis des Interviewers bloßzulegen.</note>. But above
               all »<rs type="work" ref="#29923">Der Weg in’s Freie</rs>« is remarkable for its
               brilliant, I might almost say its brutal treatment of this subject. In <rs
                  type="work" ref="#29923" subtype="implied">Heinrich <anchor type="textConst"
                     xml:id="T_I028-123"/>Beermann<note type="textConst" xml:id="T_I028-123h"><supplied>hier
                     und in Folge:</supplied><space unit="chars" quantity="1"/><quote>Behrmann</quote></note>
               </rs>, the Jewish litterateur <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> has drawn
               with such masterly dispassionate accuracy a certain type of central <rs type="place"
                  ref="#468">European</rs> Jew that I have always maintained no study of the Jewish
               question could be considered complete without a perusal of this work. <rs type="work"
                  ref="#29923" subtype="implied">Beermann</rs> is by no means a perfect being. He is
               oversensitive, self analytical, and, I am very much afraid inclined to be tactless
               yet <add place="inline">he is</add> a man of real ability and many virtues.
               Circumstances have, I think made <rs type="work" ref="#29923" subtype="implied"
                  >Beermann</rs> what he is, and though I could not get him to make a definite
               pronouncement on the subject, I am inclined <add place="above">to believe</add> that
                  <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> thinks so too. For I discussed
               Beermann with <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> just as I would discuss a
               living person. There was nothing incongruous about this, because <rs type="work"
                  ref="#29923" subtype="implied">Beermann</rs> happens to be alive. You will meet
               his like all over <rs type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs>, or for that matter with a
               slightly different accent, all over <rs type="place" ref="#151">Germany</rs>.</p>
            <p>
               <del rend="strikethrough">I </del>
               <anchor type="textConst" xml:id="TT114-3"/>
               <del rend="strikethrough">had</del>
               <note type="textConst" xml:id="TT114-3h"><quote>chd</quote></note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <del rend="strikethrough">a long talk with him one night after the opera at one of
                  those excellent <rs type="place" ref="#50">Viennise</rs> sauvage stalls. He sat
                  opposite me in the restaurant car, coming up from </del>
               <rs type="place" ref="#30">
                  <del rend="strikethrough">Salzburg</del>
               </rs>
               <del rend="strikethrough">. Incidentally he is the dramatic critic of the – but
                  perhaps that is becoming personal.</del>
               <pb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <ref type="question" target="#q088"/>
               <add place="inline">»</add>The solution of the Jewish Problem,« <add place="above"
                  >said Schnitzler</add> »is one which each individual must find for himself.
                  <anchor type="label" xml:id="L-I028-1"/><ref target="#q167" type="question"/>There
               is no general solution. Zionism does not seem to me to be a solution at all. It seems
               to me too much actuated by sudden impulses, by resentment, by a mere desire to escape
               from one’s environment and scarcely ever to spring from a well-reasoned decision.
               This does not prevent me from admiring Zionism. I admire people who can reach out so
               high and dream so splendidly, but they will never convince me.</p>
            <p><ref target="#q141" type="question"/>I need hardly point out that the Zionist plays
               actively into the hands of the anti-Semite. He confesses to a weakness in our
               position which my mind does not exist. My parents come from <rs type="place"
                  ref="#35512">Hungary</rs>, but my <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="K_I028-44"
               />desire takes me back neither to <rs type="place" ref="#35512">Hungary</rs><note
                  type="commentary" xml:id="K_I028-44h"><ref type="pointer" target="#I066_L_ungarn"
                  /></note><space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>nor <rs type="place" ref="#815"
                  >Palestine</rs>. I am rooted here in <rs type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs>, my
               home and the home of my youth. I have grown up identifying myself with the highly
               individual culture. I am part of it, and it is part of me. Why should I leave this
               country because a few ignorant and illbred fools of anti-Semites tell me I do not
               belong here?</p>
            <p>
               <ref type="question" target="#q089"/>
               <add place="inline">»</add>Do I believe that there is a basic individual Jewish
               character apart from certain traits which environment has forced upon it<subst>
                  <del rend="strikethrough">.</del>
                  <add place="inline">?</add>
               </subst> That is a difficult question<unclear>;</unclear> yet I should if anything be
               inclined to a negative <anchor type="textConst" xml:id="T_I028-1234"/>answer.<note
                  type="textConst" xml:id="T_I028-1234h"><quote>answer</quote></note> I do not
               believe that the Jew is essentially spiritually different or that there is a
               difference of spiritual rhythm between him <anchor type="textConst"
                  xml:id="T_I028-113"/>and<note type="textConst" xml:id="T_I028-113h"
                     ><quote>a</quote></note> the gentile. The attitude of the world towards him
               has produced certain psychological modifications. Take away this attitude, and those
               modifications will <subst>
                  <del rend="strikethrough">vanish. I believe every <gap quantity="9" unit="chars"
                        reason="illegible"/> of jewish parentage even of</del>
                  <add place="above">vanish. I believe that if a child of jewish parentage, even
                     of</add>
               </subst> the humblest sort, were to be taken to another country, kept in ignorance of
               its origin if that origin were also kept from its associates, that this child would
               grow up absolutely unconscious of a difference between itself and its playmates,
               except perhaps that it might develop and become<pb/> aware of a keener and quicker
               brain.</p>
            <p>
               <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="TT114-4"/>I am however compelled to admit that
               there is a sort of Freemasonary between Jews. We unconsciously feel our way to one
               another more quickly than we do to gentiles. There is a readier unspoken
               understanding. But how far this implies an actual being different on our part I
               hesitate to say.<note type="commentary" xml:id="TT114-4h">Absatz fehlt im
                  Erstdruck</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <ref type="question" target="#q141"/>Why anti-Semitism has gained so much strength
               recently? I think it has to do with the general state the world is in at present.
               Remember that a wave of hate has swept over the peoples of the <subst>
                  <del rend="strikethrough">world</del>
                  <add place="above">earth</add>
               </subst>, and that hate is a very real deep rooted instinct, which must have its vent
               once it is aroused. Some object must be found for it, and it is therefore not
               unnaturally, that it concentrates on a section of the community that enjoys a certain
               traditional privilege of persecution, a section of the community<add place="inline"
                  >,</add> moreover<add place="inline">,</add> which for some reason or other is
               weakened by an excessive objectivity and by a certain inclination to self analysis,
               and is therefore perhaps a readier victim.</p>
            <p>
               <ref type="question" target="#q091"/>Do I think that the Jews are a creative people?
               I must unhesitatingly answer that I do. Look at the names that we can show within a
               short space of time. <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="TT114-5"/>In music <rs
                  type="person" ref="#12870">Richard Strauss</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="#12163"
                  >Gustav Mahler</rs>. In painting <rs type="person" ref="#12068">Max
                  Liebermann</rs>, in literature a whole host of names.<note type="commentary"
                  xml:id="TT114-5h">Das fehlt im Erstdruck, weil <rs type="person" ref="#12870"
                     >Strauss</rs> kein Jude war. Oberhalb von <rs type="person" ref="#12870"
                     >Strauss</rs> ein unentziffertes handschriftliches Wort, wahrscheinlich von <rs
                     type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>, eben dies bemängelnd.</note> More
               than that I believe we are on the verge of great Jewish renaissance. <anchor
                  type="commentary" xml:id="K_I028-4"/>What the artistic<note type="commentary"
                  xml:id="K_I028-4h">Ab hier ist der Text handschriftlich geschrieben.</note>
               message is that Judaism has to deliver I do not<pb/> know, but there is a promise of
               something in the air. Any man with a feeling for these things must become aware of
               it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biographical">
            <div1>
               <ref type="schnitzlerDiary" target="1923-11-12"/>
               <quote>– Mr. <rs type="person" ref="#14026">J. L. Benvenisti</rs> (<rs type="place"
                     ref="#224">London</rs>) unvermutetes <rs type="work" ref="#32995"
                        subtype="implied">Interview</rs> (<rs type="work" ref="#29923">Heinrich
                     Bermann</rs>, Zionismus,– <rs type="person" ref="#12819">Spengler</rs>,
                  Causalität, Schicksal etc. –).</quote>
            </div1>
            <div1>
               <ref type="schnitzlerDiary" target="1924-01-24"/>
               <quote>Hr. <rs type="person" ref="#14026">Benvenisti</rs>; brachte mir das <rs
                     type="work" ref="#32995" subtype="implied">Interview</rs> (englisch), das er
                  über mich geschrieben.</quote>
            </div1>
            <div1>
               <bibl>
                  <rs type="person" ref="#14026">Benvenisti</rs> an <rs type="person" ref="#2121"
                     >Schnitzler</rs>, <date>16.&#8239;5.&#8239;[1924]</date>
               </bibl>
               <quote>
                  <p>
                     <date>May 16.</date>
                  </p>
                  <p>Dear D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Schnitzler</p>
                  <p>The interview you so kindly granted me appeared in <rs type="place" ref="#175"
                        >America</rs> some time ago, and a copy of it has been for weeks following
                     me over <rs type="place" ref="#468">Europe</rs>. As the delay has already been
                     considerable, I do sincerely hope you will not be angry with me for sending
                     this copy, the only copy I have at present to D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <rs type="person" ref="#10872">Benedict</rs>, who told me that he might perhaps
                     want to use it, but whom I have requested to pass the copy on to you when he
                     has done with it. <hi rend="underline" n="1">I have, however, written to </hi><rs
                        type="place" ref="#175"><hi rend="underline" n="1">America</hi></rs>
                      for further copies and hope to be able to send one on to you in about a
                     fortnight.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="outOfScope" unit="paragraphs" quantity="1"/>
                  </p>
                  <p>I am glad to say that my stupid mistake in making you refer to 
                        <rs type="person" ref="#12870"><hi rend="underline" n="1">Strauss</hi></rs>
                      as a Jew did not appear in print, otherwise the interview was printed as
                     in the copy submitted to you, except for a few trifling excisions.</p>
                  <p>Do <hi rend="underline" n="1">please</hi> believe that I shall always bear in
                     mind the great kindness and interest you showed me while I was in <rs
                        type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs>.</p>
                  <p>I remain Yours sincerely</p>
                  <p>JLBenvenisti</p></quote>
            </div1>
            <div1>
               <ref type="schnitzlerDiary" target="1924-10-30"/>
               <quote>Vm. Hr. <rs type="person" ref="#14026">Benvenisti</rs> (<rs type="place"
                     ref="#224">London</rs>) der indess zum Katholizismus übergetreten ist, an die
                  Dogmen glaubt, auch an <rs type="place" ref="#49133">Lourdes</rs> (nachdem
                  kürzlich sein <rs type="work" ref="#32995" subtype="implied">Interview</rs> mit
                  mir über den Zionismus im <rs type="org" ref="#29410">Amer. Hebrew</rs> erschienen
                  ist). Wir spazierten eine Weile auch im Freien.–</quote>
            </div1>
            <div1>
               <ref type="schnitzlerDiary" target="1925-03-03"/>
               <quote>Vm. <rs type="person" ref="#13191">Otto Zoff</rs> (wegen des <rs type="work"
                     ref="#32995" subtype="implied">Artikels</rs> von <rs type="person" ref="#14026"
                     >Benvenisti</rs> über mich, wogegen ich einiges zu erinnern habe).</quote>
            </div1>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
