<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../meta/asischema.xsd"
   xml:base="schnitzler-interviews" xml:id="I030">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="s">Arthur Schnitzler: Interviews</title>
            <title level="a" ref="#32999">David Ewen: Schnitzler Tells Why He Is a Jew,
               27.&#8239;8.&#8239;1931</title>
            <author ref="#11277">Ewen, David</author>
            <editor>
               <name>Müller, Martin Anton</name>
            </editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>ASI</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transkription und Kommentierung</resp>
               <name>Martin Anton Müller</name>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Martin Anton Müller</publisher>
            <idno type="asi" n="030"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listBibl>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="#2121">Schnitzler, Arthur</author>
                     <title level="a" ref="#32999">Schnitzler Tells Why</title>
                     <editor>As told to David Ewen</editor>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j" ref="#57978">The American Israelite</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="1931-08-27" n="1">27.&#8239;8.&#8239;1931</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="vol">78</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="nr">8</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">1, 5</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="#2121">Schnitzler, Arthur</author>
                     <title level="a" ref="#32999">Why I am a Jew</title>
                     <editor>As told to David Ewen</editor>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j" ref="#58355">The Canadian Jewish Chronicle</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="1931-08-28" n="1">28.&#8239;8.&#8239;1931</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="jg">19</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="nr">15</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">3</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="#2121">Schnitzler, Arthur</author>
                     <title level="a">Why I am a Jew</title>
                     <editor>As told to David Ewen</editor>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j">The Jewish Advocate</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="1931-09-11" n="1">11.&#8239;9.&#8239;1931</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="vol">61</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="nr">11</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="sec">7</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">1</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en-US">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="approved">
         <change who="MAM" when="2017-11-17">angelegt</change>
         <change who="MAM" when="2018-02-14">Index check</change>
         <change who="MAM" when="2019-02-13">Durchsicht nach Amer. Israelite</change>
         <change who="KH" when="2021-11-02">Durchsicht</change>
         <change who="MAM" when="2021-11-03">Korrekturen nach AI</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="text">
      <body>
         <div type="original" xml:lang="en-US">
            <head>Schnitzler <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="K_I030-1"/>Tells Why<note
                  type="commentary" xml:id="K_I030-1h">die Fortsetzung auf S. 5 nennt einen längeren
                  Titel: »<quote>Schnitzler Tells Why he is a Jew</quote>«</note>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">By <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">As told to David Ewen</head>
            <p>
               <ref type="question" target="#q143"/>(Many of us would be hard put to give an
               adequate answer to the question »why are you a Jew.« <rs type="person" ref="#2121"
                  >Arthur Schnitzler</rs>, the world famous novelist answers that question in this
               exclusive interview obtained for <rs type="work" ref="#57978">
                  <hi rend="small_caps">The Israelite</hi>
               </rs> and the <rs type="org" ref="#57981">Jewish Telegraphic Agency</rs>).</p>
            <p rend="center">–</p>
            <p>Some of us are Jews only because of an accident of birth. We are Jews only because we
               were born Jews. Others of us, however, are Jews for a much more potent reason. We
               feel our race deeply within us, we react keenly and sensitively to it, we think ever
               in terms of it; That is of a greater importance in branding us Jews than any accident
               of birth can be.</p>
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs>, one of the greatest living
               literary figures in the world, is one of the latter. He is one of our most desirable
               Jews. Although he is primarily a novelist and a dramatist – one of the world’s finest
               – he has time and again lent an eager pen for the cause of Judaism. </p>
            <p>In play-form he has given us »<rs type="work" ref="#30203">Prof. Bernhardi</rs>« –
               one of the most vicious attacks against the stupidity of anti-Semitism yet penned. In
               novel-form he has given us the »<rs type="work" ref="#29923">Open Road</rs>«, in
               which Jewish problems are discussed with penetration, lucidity and power. </p>
            <p>Besides this, there remains the mountain of articles which he has contributed in
               order to clarify the position of the Jew in the modern world, and to attempt to
               explain to him his inmost problems.</p>
            <head type="sub">Schnitzler Tells Why</head>
            <p>It was to talk about Judaism that I came to visit <rs type="person" ref="#2121"
                  >Arthur Schnitzler</rs> in his spacious home in a suburb of <rs type="place"
                  ref="#50">Vienna</rs>. And speak about Judaism he did in great detail, for it is
               ever near to his heart. But most important of all he clearly explained to me why it
               is that he is a Jew.</p>
            <p>»If I am today deeply interested in my race,« he said, »the outstanding reason is not
               because I was born a Jew. Strange to say, as far as I am concerned, this is the most
               negligible reason of all. True, if I had not been born a Jew I could not today have
               been a staunch advocate of my race; that is self-evident. And yet, I must add that
               accident of birth I feel has been the most negligible reason of all in making me
               race-conscious. It was the most negligible influence of all in driving me ultimately
               in the acceptance and in instilling into me a profound interest in and appreciation
               for my race. </p>
            <p>»There are those who, born to strictly pious parents, have been rigidly inculcated in
               Jewish principles and dogmas. Such people, it can be said, are Jews because they were
               born Jews. But with me it is altogether different. My <rs type="person" ref="#12695"
                  >father</rs>, a very gifted and famous physician, had very slight connections with
               his race. Religious education never entered into my early life; religious thought of
               any kind never influenced it in the least. And so, in the early years of my life,
               which stretched well beyond my adolescence, I could hardly be <anchor
                  type="commentary" xml:id="K_I030-2"/>called a Jew<note type="commentary"
                  xml:id="K_I030-2h">der Zweitdruck ergänzt am Satzende: »<quote>, although I was
                     born one</quote>«</note>.</p>
            <head type="sub">Objects To Chauvinism</head>
            <p>»Why I am a Jew? Certainly, it is not because I think that Jewish culture is the
               greatest of all possible cultures or because I feel that the Jew is the greatest of
               all possible human beings. </p>
            <p>»Chauvinism of any kind whatsoever, I have always felt keenly, is unforgiveably
               stupid. It is true, of course, that it is the tendency of a persecuted race to be
               chauvinistic, especially if it has sensitivity, culture and sensibilities. That is
               why the Jew must always exert especial care in avoiding it. For chauvinism, after
               all, defeats its own purpose. You cannot convince anyone of your profound
               capabilities if you are continually trumpeting about them through bugles. Let your
               actions speak louder than any words! </p>
            <p>»Yes, we may be proud of our racial heritage and of our history, we may refuse ever
               to conceal our identity; but modesty is always an enviable virtue. True, I have in
               recent years come to realize that there is a unique importance to Jewish culture and
               that the Jew contributed much to the world of thought. But every man of learning
               realizes that the Jew has not been alone in this respect. We must always remember
               that the Jew is only one part of a great civilization.</p>
            <head type="sub">The Path Of Persecution</head>
            <p>»Why, then, am I a Jew? I am a Jew, first of all, because foreign influences have
               driven me <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="K_I030-17"/>willy-nilly<note
                  type="commentary" xml:id="K_I030-17h">amerikanisches Englisch: geradewohl</note>
               to my faith. I am certain that if I were living in the best of all possible worlds
               where race-hatred, anti-Semitism, Jew-baiting were all unspeakable and unheard of, I
               would no more be conscious of my faith than the most stout-hearted skeptic. In such a
               world, I am sure, race consciousness would be of very little importance or necessity.
               It would, as a matter of fact, be diminished a hundred fold. But since we are not
               living in such a world, conditions everywhere have driven me into a greater and
               greater race-consciousness.</p>
            <p>»I was first made aware of the fact that I was a Jew during my <rs type="place"
                  ref="#386">university</rs> days, when, as a member of a <anchor type="commentary"
                  xml:id="KT116-1"/>philanthropic society<note type="commentary" xml:id="KT116-1h">
                  <ref target="#L_KT118-1" type="pointer"/>
               </note> which meted out sparse charity to needy students, I was made aware of the
               fact that Jewish students were openly discriminated against. That made a profound
               impression upon me. It opened my eyes to a condition which had always existed but to
               which I had been as blind as a mole. </p>
            <p>»From that time on I realized how much injustice, how much blind and hot-tempered
               hate, how much bitterness and stupidity were levelled against the Jew. </p>
            <p>»Always an ally of the oppressed, I became once and for all deeply interested in the
               Jew. Jewish problems became my own intimate problems. I absorbed myself with Jewish
               thought and culture. I had become, suddenly, a Jew in heart and in soul.</p>
            <head type="sub">Drawn To Jewish Studies</head>
            <p>»Of course there must be other <pb/>reasons why I am a Jew. I might point to the fact
               that my studies in Jewish history, culture and thought have awakened something deep
               within me and that I have found something of myself in them. I might point to the
               fact that I have come to realize that the problems of the Jew affect not only people
               very near to me, but affect me personally as well. This, much more than any accident
               of birth, has made me a Jew.</p>
            <p>»I might add, in conclusion, that being a Jew requires a consummate grace and tact. I
               have already spoken about the stupidity of chauvinism. </p>
            <p>»But chauvinism is not half so bad as a complete indifference to and an avoidance of
               Jewish interests. A Jew should strive to attain something of a golden mean: modest
               and unassuming at some times, but loud-voiced when the emergency presents itself.
               That is the type of Jew I have always strived to be.«</p>
            <p rend="center">(Copyright <rs type="org" ref="#57981">Jewish Tel. Agency</rs>)</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biographical">
            <div1>
               <ref type="schnitzlerDiary" target="1930-08-15"/>
               <quote>Nm. <rs type="person" ref="#11277">David Ewes</rs>, junger Journalist <rs
                     type="place" ref="#44053">New York</rs>, dem ich ein Interview abgeschlagen;
                  Gespräch.–</quote>
            </div1>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
