<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../meta/asischema.xsd"
     xml:base="schnitzler-interviews"
     xml:id="I074">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="s">Arthur Schnitzler: »Das Zeitlose ist von kürzester Dauer.« Interviews, Meinungen, Proteste (1891–1931)</title>
            <title level="a" ref="#58149">Merryle Rukeyser: Financial Advice to a Young Man (Ausschnitt), 1927</title>
            <author ref="#23729">Rukeyser, Merryle Stanley</author>
            <editor>
               <name>Müller, Martin Anton</name>
            </editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>ASI</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transkription und Kommentierung</resp>
               <name>Martin Anton Müller</name>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Martin Anton Müller</publisher>
            <idno type="asi" n="074"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listBibl>
               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author ref="#23729">Rukeyser, Merryle Stanley</author>
                     <title level="m" ref="#58149">Financial Advice to a Young Man. A Program for Getting Along
                        in the World</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="1927-01-01" n="1">1927</date>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Simon and Schuster</publisher>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">77–79</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en-US">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="approved">
         <change who="MAM" when="2019-02-13">angelegt</change>
         <change who="MAM" when="2021-09-06">Index check</change>
         <change who="KH" when="2021-10-27">Durchsicht</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="text">
      <body>
         <div type="original"  xml:lang="en-US">
            <head>Recreation in Varied Work</head>
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="#12314">Benito Mussolini</rs> recently told the world that he
               works sixteen hours a day.</p>
            <p>Shallow minded observers will conclude that, if such a, program is feasible for <rs type="person" subtype="implied" ref="#12314">Il Duce</rs>, it is practicable for the ordinary
               workingman.</p>
            <p>The deduction would be fallacious even if the premise stands as correct.</p>
            <p>The <rs type="person" ref="#12314" subtype="implied">Premier</rs> of <rs type="place" ref="#40306">Italy</rs> has varied and interesting work, which ever stirs anew his creative
               instincts and his boundless energies. His daily chores, full of high adventure and
               the stimulus of leadership, are not to be compared with the monotonous routine of the
               factory worker.</p>
            <p>The great human problem in connection with machine civilization is to minimize the
               monotony and <pb/> drudgery of toilers who must repeat through the day a single,
               simple process. In an earlier period when hand work prevailed, the worker had the
               creative thrill of making a product from the start to the finish. The worker in the
               modern factory contributes only a single step in the process.</p>
            <p>Non-routine workers are not to be compared with those in the factory.</p>
            <p>I visited <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs> at <rs type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs> last summer, <ref type="question" target="#q013"/>and discussed his methods with him. When he
               tires of a play on which he may be working, that veteran author turns to an essay.
               When his attention begins to lag, he lays that aside, and does some work on a novel.
               Then he may shift to a short story. He usually produces at least four works of art at
               the same time, finding relaxation in turning from one to another.</p>
            <p>The human mind loves variety; it loathes monotony.</p>
            <p>Personnel directors in modern business establishments should recognize the wisdom in
               breaking up tedium either with recesses or rest periods, or preferably by shifting
               workers at intervals from one task to another.</p>
            <p>With immigration restricted, employers are coming to understand the need of
               economizing labor, which receives high wages. The real need is not to get
               work<pb/>ers to put in hours, but to keep them interested while they are at work.</p>
            <p>The field, which is still virgin, offers large opportunities for cooperation between
               practical business men and psychologists.</p>
            <p>After work, the wise individual who recognizes the restfulness of variety will find
               fuller ways to use leisure time, which is too frequently frittered away.</p>
            <p>The trite expression, »variety is the spice of life« is in accordance with the
               findings of psychologists and the experience of leaders in commerce and in art.</p>
            <p>Seeing new scenery and new faces on vacations has a tonic effect. It stimulates the
               imagination and tones up an individual.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biographical">
            <div1>
               <ref type="schnitzlerDiary" target="1926-07-12"/>
               <quote>Mr. <rs type="person" ref="#23729">Merryle S. Rukeyser</rs> aus <rs type="place" ref="#44053">New York</rs>; eigentlich ein Interview.–</quote>
            </div1>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
