<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../../XML/meta/asischema.xsd"
   xml:base="schnitzler-interviews" xml:id="I087">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="s">Arthur Schnitzler: Interviews</title>
            <title level="a" ref="#58559">Karl Schauermann: Old Vienna Goes American,
               18.&#8239;12.&#8239;1928</title>
            <author ref="#24073">Schauermann, Karl</author>
            <editor>
               <name>Müller, Martin Anton</name>
            </editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>ASI</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transkription und Kommentierung</resp>
               <name>Martin Anton Müller</name>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Martin Anton Müller</publisher>
            <idno type="asi" n="087"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listBibl>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="#24073">Schauermann, Karl</author>
                     <title level="a" ref="#58559">Old Vienna goes American</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j" ref="#58558">Milwaukee Journal</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="1928-12-18" n="1">18.&#8239;12.&#8239;1928</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="sec">II</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">4</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en-US">Englisch</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="approved">
         <change who="MAM" when="2018-10-19">angelegt aus Julia Glunks Abschrift</change>
         <change who="MAM" when="2021-09-22">Index check</change>
         <change who="KH" when="2021-10-27">Durchsicht</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="text">
      <body>
         <div type="original" xml:lang="en-US">
            <head>»Old <rs type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs> Goes American«.</head>
            <head type="sub">Schnitzler, Playwright and Novelist, Says His Countrymen Have Acquired
               All of <rs type="place" ref="#43406">U. S.</rs> Habits Except Energy and
               Success</head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Arthur Schnitzler, <rs type="place" ref="#50">Viennese</rs>
                  playwright and novelist, an interview with whom is reported below by Karl
                  Scheuermann, a <rs type="org" ref="#56586">Milwaukee newspaper</rs> man, is one of
                  the chief figures in contemporary continental literature. In <rs type="place"
                     ref="#175">America</rs>, however, he is more widely known for his novels, many
                  of which have been translated from the German, than he is for his plays. Among the
                  former are »<rs type="work" ref="#29941">Fraulein Else</rs>,« »<rs type="work"
                     ref="#36048">Beatrice</rs>,« »<rs type="work" ref="#30851">Rhapsody</rs>« and
                     »<rs type="work" ref="#30817">Therese</rs>,« of which the last named is his
                  longest and was published this fall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Complications greet the interviewer who would see <rs type="person" ref="#2121"
                  >Arthur Schnitzler</rs>, internationally known playwright and novelist, at his
               home in <rs type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs>. For Herr <rs type="person"
                  ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>, like most famous and much bothered men, is not at
               home to everybody and to guard against casual interruptions at his work has a silent
               telephone number. Although I have carried on a correspondence with him for a matter
               of 15 years or more, it was necessary for me to go through the formality of calling
               at his home, <rs type="place" ref="#150">Sternwartestrasse 71</rs>, inquiring for his
               telephone number and then making the telephonic introduction, which he requires, at
               an appointed time.</p>
            <p>Yes, he would be glad to see me he said – sometime within the next day or two. The
               following morning Mr. <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> called to say he
               would chat with me for an hour or so at <time>6 30</time> that evening.</p>
            <p>The thing that struck me about the author of »<rs type="work" ref="#29935"
                  >Anatole</rs>,« »<rs type="work" ref="#29855">Reigen</rs>,« »<anchor type="commentary" xml:id="K_I087-12"/><rs type="work"
                     ref="#29917">Light o Love</rs><note type='commentary' xml:id="K_I087-12h"><rs type="work"
                        ref="#29917">Liebelei</rs></note>,« as he stepped from a room on the second floor of
               his carefully groomed villa, was his grayness. A gray beard that had grown beyond the
               well defined outlines of a <rs type="person" ref="#15581">Van Dyke</rs>; <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="K_I087-2"/>gray blue
               eyes<note type='commentary' xml:id="K_I087-2h"><ref type="pointer" target="#L_I102_augen"/></note> below gray brows and squinting lids: a gray mane combed from the right side of
               the massive head toward the left ear; a gray blue cutaway that seemed almost too
               tight for shoulders chunky rather than broad and indicative of a life at the desk
               rather than on football grounds.</p>
            <p>I recalled his liking for gray from his letters – his <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="K_I087-14"/>stationery<note type='commentary' xml:id="K_I087-14h"><rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>s Briefpapier
            hatte zeitweise einen bläulich-grauen Ton, doch ändert sich das über die Jahre und lässt sich keine
            Vorliebe für eine bestimmte Papierfarbe feststellen.</note> was of that color. I
               was reminded at the same time that here was no longer the <rs type="person"
                  ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> of the »<rs type="work" ref="#29935">Anatole</rs>«
               days but a man past 60, careworn and wincing under the reality of death, the same
               death with which he has toyed in so many of his plays and novels and which, a few
               months ago, took from him his beloved daughter.</p>
            <p>Mr <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> did not sit long at a time during
               our chat of two hours or so. He likes to stand or move about while he talks and this
               is his habit also when he is busy on a new novel or play. Mr <rs type="person"
                  ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> stands there speaking with a voice of extremely
               musical timbre and with a precision of intonation and liveliness of tempo that bear
               no suggestion of the <rs type="place" ref="#50">Viennese</rs> or <rs type="place"
                  ref="#41240">Austrian</rs> »I should worry« attitude. He agreed with me that the
               much talked about geniality and social gracefulness of the <rs type="place" ref="#50"
                  >Viennese</rs> are but surface elements, that the <rs type="place" ref="#50"
                  >Viennese</rs> is spending too much of his time in the coffee house and that the
               traditional »Schlamperei« in public offices has grown rather than decreased in the 10
               years that <rs type="place" ref="#41240">Austria</rs> has been a republic. Holidays
               are declared on every pretext.</p>
            <p>»We seem to have so much time here,« said <rs type="person" ref="#2121"
                  >Schnitzler</rs>, »but have we? Compared with <rs type="place" ref="#151"
                  >Germany</rs> we are making slow progress in our reconstruction work. There are
               too many officials. It seems people must be employed somehow.«</p>
            <p>I have observed that the only time when a <rs type="place" ref="#50">Viennese</rs>
               has no time is when he has to make, or thinks he has to make, an electric train or
               street car. He will chase after it for a block and swing onto it with an athletic
               experience that is as remarkable as it is suicidal. Now police authorities are
               considering energetic steps to stop the nuisance which, clearly visible legends in
               all street cars inform you, is strictly prohibited by law.</p>
            <p>Mr <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>, by the way, considers railroad and
               electric train riding the most dangerous transportation hazards, more so than a
               trans-Atlantic boat trip. He would rather fly than float, and feels himself nowhere
               safer than when in an airship.</p>
            <p>
               <ref type="question" target="#q130"/>»I wouldn't mind a trip to <rs type="place"
                  ref="#175">America</rs> but for the railroad distances. Once in <rs type="place"
                  ref="#175">America</rs> I would want to see all. <rs type="place" ref="#44053">New
                  York</rs> alone wouldn't do. I have been approached several times by lecture tour
               managers but the financial reward offered does not warrant the effort.«</p>
            <p>Which brought the conversation to the chronic emptiness of the <rs type="place"
                  ref="#41240">Austrian</rs> pocketbook and the tremendous influence <rs
                  type="place" ref="#175">American</rs> financial and industrial supremacy is having
               upon all phases of life in <rs type="place" ref="#468">Europe</rs> today.</p>
            <p>»Anything and everything <rs type="place" ref="#175">American</rs> is above par, in
               the public’s imagination as well as in the realities of the market,« said <rs
                  type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>. »We imitate and adopt <rs type="place"
                  ref="#175">American</rs> clothes, <rs type="place" ref="#175">American</rs> music,
                  <rs type="place" ref="#175">American</rs> plays, <rs type="place" ref="#175"
                  >American</rs> films, <rs type="place" ref="#175">American</rs> traffic rules, <rs
                  type="place" ref="#175">American</rs> sports, <rs type="place" ref="#175"
                  >American</rs> everything except <rs type="place" ref="#175">American</rs> energy
               and success.«</p>
            <p>Of <rs type="place" ref="#175">American</rs> plays that are now »packing ’em in« over
               here Mr. <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> had in mind »<rs type="work"
                  ref="#58219">Broadway</rs>,« »<rs type="work" ref="#58214">Chicago</rs>,« »<rs
                  type="work" ref="#58226">An American Tragedy</rs>,« »<rs type="work" ref="#58208"
                  >The Trial of Mary Dugan</rs>.«</p>
            <p>»It is only seldom that I go to a theater,« the writer of world renowned plays
               declared. »I would go to concerts in years gone, my natural artistic inclination
               being decidedly more toward music than the stage. However, I am a keen frequenter of
               the kino (movie) as it permits one to come and go as one pleases and gives one many
               things that are not possible on the stage. I have seen quite a number of <rs
                  type="place" ref="#175">American</rs> films. There was a time when <rs
                  type="place" ref="#175">American</rs> pictures were poor, but that time is of the
               past.«</p>
            <p>There are several persons whom Mr <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> would
               like to meet should he come to <rs type="place" ref="#175">America</rs>. One is a
                  <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="K_I087-1"/><rs type="person" ref="#24825"
                     subtype="implied">publisher</rs><note type="commentary" xml:id="K_I087-1h"><anchor type="label" xml:id="Label-K_I087-1"/><rs
                     type="person" ref="#24825">Thomas Seltzer</rs>, der <date>1922</date> das Werk
                  zuerst in einer teureren Ausgabe von 3.000 Stück, dann nachdem alle Exemplare
                  verkauft waren, im Folgejahr eine günstigere Ausgabe mit einer Auflage von 3–5.000
                  Stück publizierte, die nach kurzer Zeit um weitere 3.000 erweitert wurde. Bereits
                  für die erste Ausgabe beschränkte sich <rs type="person" ref="#24825"
                  >Seltzer</rs>s Überweisung auf 200 Dollar Anzahlung und 500 Dollar Bezahlung, nur
                  ein Teil der zustehenden Summe, die <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>
                  am <date>1.&#160;6.&#160;1923</date> in einem Brief an den Verleger mit 1.200
                  Dollar bezifferte. Auch nach Zahlung durch den Verlag musste <rs type="person"
                     ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> mehrmals urgieren, um weitere Beträge zu erhalten.
                  In Folge engagierte den Rechtsanwalt <rs type="person" ref="#25465">Benjamin
                     Stern</rs>, um zu seinem Recht zu kommen, doch noch <date>1926</date> musste
                     <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> ausstehende Zahlungen einfordern.
                     <rs type="person" ref="#25465">Stern</rs> antwortete entgegen der Darstellung
                  in diesem Interview sehr wohl, brachte aber die Sache nicht, wie von <rs
                     type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> gewünscht, zu einem Abschluss.</note>
               who, he said, paid him a pittance for the limited number edition of »<rs type="work"
                  ref="#42883">Casanova’s Homecoming</rs>,« and the other a <rs type="place"
                  ref="#44053">New York</rs>
               <rs subtype="implied" ref="#25465" type="person">lawyer</rs> whom he had engaged to
               prosecute the publisher but from whom he heard nothing after the first exchange of
               courtesies.</p>
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> by the way, is <anchor
                  type="commentary" xml:id="K_I087-4"/>still a practicing physician<note
                  type="commentary" xml:id="K_I087-4h">Das ist auszuschließen, höchstens, dass er
                     sich im Familien- und Freundeskreis betätigte.</note>, the
               profession which he followed exclusively before his success as a dramatist and
               novelist. Not a few of his plays are built around themes which have grown out of his
               medical experience. At the literary <rs type="org" ref="#36247">Burg theater</rs>
               <!-- sic! --> in <rs type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs> his most frequently played
               drama is »<rs type="work" ref="#29937">Der Junge Medardus</rs>,« followed by »<rs
                  type="work" ref="#30207">Das Weite Land</rs>« and »<rs type="work" ref="#30205"
                  >Komoedie der Verfuehrung</rs>.«</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biographical">
            <div1>
               <ref target="1928-11-15" type="schnitzlerDiary"/>
               <quote>Nach 6 Hr. <rs type="person" ref="#24073">Schauermann</rs> aus <rs
                     type="place" ref="#49803">Milwaukee</rs>, Corresp. vor etwa 20 Jahren. Gegen
                  50; hat seinen <rs type="person" ref="#58562" subtype="implied">Vater</rs> in <rs
                     type="place" ref="#58556">Coblenz</rs> besucht. Journalist, Lehrer, Dramatiker
                  (?);– verheiratet, <rs type="person" ref="#58567 #58571" subtype="implied">2 Kinder</rs>, <rs
                     type="person" ref="#58565" subtype="implied">Frau</rs>?– Diese Reise wie es
                  scheint vielfach aus innern Gründen.– Schien bewegt von eignem Schicksal und
                  meinem.</quote>
            </div1>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
