<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../../XML/meta/asischema.xsd"
   xml:base="schnitzler-interviews" xml:id="I088">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="s">Arthur Schnitzler: Interviews</title>
            <title level="a" ref="#58593">Reuben Brainin: Schnitzler, 26.&#8239;6.&#8239;1931</title>
            <author ref="#14472">Brainin, Reuben</author>
            <editor>
               <name>Müller, Martin Anton</name>
            </editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>ASI</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transkription und Kommentierung</resp>
               <name>Martin Anton Müller</name>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Martin Anton Müller</publisher>
            <idno type="asi" n="088"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listBibl>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="#14472">Brainin, Reuben</author>
                     <title level="a" ref="#58593">Schnitzler</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j" ref="#58324">The Jewish Chronicle</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="1931-06-26" n="1">26. 6. 1931</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="vol">21</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="nr">14</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">2</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en-US">Englisch</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="approved">
         <change who="MAM" when="2018-10-19">angelegt aus Julia Glunks Abschrift</change>
         <change who="MAM" when="2021-09-15">Index check</change>
         <change who="KH" when="2021-11-02">Durchsicht</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="text">
      <body>
         <div type="original" xml:lang="en-US">
            <head>
               <rs type="person" ref="#2121">
                  <hi rend="capitals">Schnitzler</hi>
               </rs>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Skeptic of <rs type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">By Reuben Brainin</head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">The literary world is celebrating the seventieth year of Arthur
                     <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>, one of the foremost
                  story-tellers of our time. Reuben Brainin, dean of Hebrew literature, and a
                     <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="K_I088-1"/>personal friend<note
                     type="commentary" xml:id="K_I088-1h">Im <rs type="work" ref="#33243"
                        >Tagebuch</rs> ist nur das in Folge erwähnte Treffen am <ref
                        target="1903-10-02" type="schnitzlerDiary" subtype="date-only"/>
                        festgehalten: »<quote>Brainin Nm., <rs type="place" ref="#34438">russ.</rs>
                        Jude. Neu Hebr. Zeitschrift. Zustände in <rs type="place" ref="#34438"
                           >Rußland</rs>.– Der jüd. Arbeiter, der (wie so viele) als Dachdecker der
                           <rs type="place" ref="#34438">russ.</rs> Kirche das Kreuz anbringt und Kolnidre dazu singt.</quote>«</note> of
                     <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>, here gives an appreciation of
                  the Austrian Jewish author as he understands him – as a man, a writer and a Jew. –
                  The Editor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the beginning of the twentieth century <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur
                  Schnitzler</rs>’s most famous writings were his »<rs type="work" ref="#29935"
                  >Anatol</rs>,« »<rs type="work" ref="#29917">Liebelei</rs>,« »<rs type="work"
                  ref="#30117">Sterben</rs>,« »<rs type="work" ref="#29853">Leutenant Gustl</rs>.« A
               light sort of writing, in form and in content. Dialogues: between people of elegant
               manners and wellmanicured ideas; between graceful and polite sentimentalists; between
               people disappointed in love but still hunting for the supreme thrill: between
               intellectual esthetes unfit for the hardships of life, with too soft hands and
               backbones; between women who avidly seek the perfect lover and try to escape the
               everyday drabness of their prosaic existence. And above the tribulations and often
               petty tragedies of <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>’s puppets there
               always hung the cloud of inevitable death, which whipped them into life and yet, at
               the same time, paralyzed them. The thought of the end, which made them realize the
               futility of love and yet drove them on to find that elusive something which might
               cheat the Grim Reaper of his victim. This is the essence of <rs type="person"
                  ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>’s first literary decade. But to that should be added a
               fine, skeptical, often ironic smile, the smile of <rs type="person" ref="#2121"
                  >Arthur Schnitzler</rs> who, instead of pitying his contemporaries, just looks at
               them sadly as they struggle against their fate. A smile that makes us weep.</p>
            <p>I still remember my surprise when I met <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur
                  Schnitzler</rs> for the first time at <rs type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs>, in
                  <date>September, 1903</date>. I had expected to find a snob, an elegant idler, a
               middle-aged »<rs type="work" ref="#29935">Anatol</rs>.« His reputation – conceptions
               of authors by readers are mostly misleading – was that of a polished, brilliant and
               rather superficial literateur in his personal life. But the <rs type="person"
                  ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> I met, then in his forties, impressed me much more as
               a scholar than as a novelist in vogue. His medical training – <rs type="person"
                  ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> is a graduate physician and for some years was
               attached to a <rs type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs> hospital – had influenced him
               strongly. His interest in <anchor type="textConst" xml:id="T_I088-1"/>psychology<note
                  type="textConst" xml:id="T_I088-1h"><quote>psychoolgy</quote></note> was that of
               a man of science. When he spoke of people and of sociological currents it was in the
               language of a sober observer, a studious research worker and a pitiless prober. It
               had been his lot, as a physician, to handle a human species naked, without official
               garb, without the distinction of rank. He had found himself almost in the role of a
               spiritual and physical father confessor. During our conversation, on my first visit
               to him, we spoke primarily of the Jewish renaissance movement and the awakening of
               the Jewish national consciousness. He modestly assumed the role of the listener eager
               to be informed. There were moments when he struck me as pedantic, rather too serious,
               almost solemn.</p>
            <p>In later years, at subsequent meetings, my first impressions were merely confirmed<c
                  rendition="#dots" n="3"/>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs> the man was the very antithesis
               of the dandy the intelligentsia of <rs type="place" ref="#468">Europe</rs> visualized
               him. It was the old trap into which readers fall so readily – that of shaping the
               author in accordance with the personages or heroes of his works – which was
               responsible for the distorted legend that had been created around <rs type="person"
                  ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs> the <rs type="place" ref="#50">Viennese</rs>
               author.</p>
            <p>You will ask me: »But to what extent is <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur
                  Schnitzler</rs> a Jew?« If you will forgive me – the question is rather
               unnecessary and petty. Jewishness cannot be measured in doses or percentages. And
               surely not when it comes to a personality like <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur
                  Schnitzler</rs>, with so distinct an outlook upon life. Born at <rs type="place"
                  ref="#50">Vienna</rs>, of what we are wont to call an assimilated family – his
               father was a distinguished physician and a Professor at the <rs type="org"
                  ref="#52775">University of Vienna</rs> – <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur
                  Schnitzler</rs> although he personally did not experience any virulent
               anti-Semitism, clearly recognized the anomalous position of the <rs type="place"
                  ref="#41240">Austrian</rs> Jew. He pondered on the Jewish question long and
               sincerely. He gathered material laboriously. When, <anchor type="commentary"
                  xml:id="K_I088-12"/>a year before the world war<note type="commentary"
                  xml:id="K_I088-12h">Die Uraufführung fand am <ref target="1912-11-28"
                     type="schnitzlerDiary" subtype="date-only"/> statt.</note>, he published »<rs
                  type="work" ref="#30203">Professor Bernhardi</rs>,« a play centering around a
               medical <rs type="person" ref="#4216">Dreyfus</rs> case and exposing the anti-Semitic
               tendencies in <rs type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs>’s medical and government
               circles, he stamped himself as a foe of the assimilationist movement.</p>
            <p>But the story of <rs type="work" ref="#30203">Professor Bernhardi</rs> is told with
               an ironic smile. No attempt is made to effect a reform; nor is the author inclined to
               let his indignation get the best of him. The last word before the curtain goes down
               is characteristic of <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>. Somehow it leaves
               you doubtful as to whether <rs type="work" ref="#30203">Professor Bernhardi</rs>, who
               was condemned to two months in jail because he forbade a priest to give absolution to
               a patient, was an idealist or merely a fool. None the less the play created a furore
               and showed clearly where <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> stood with
               regard to his Jewishness. No more ruthless caricature of the assimilated and
               converted Jew has been written than <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>’s
                  »<rs type="work" ref="#30203">Professor Bernhardi</rs>.«</p>
            <p>Thus <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> is inscribed in the German
               literary Who’s Who as a Jewish author, although – except in »<rs type="work"
                  ref="#30203">Professor Bernhardi</rs>« and his novel »<rs type="work" ref="#29923"
                  >Der Weg Ins Freie</rs>« – he has not concerned himself with Jewish questions. He
               was satisfied to write of the <rs type="place" ref="#50">Viennese</rs>, of the
               sentimental, romantic loves of half-baked girls, of elegant officers, of
               disillusioned servant girls, derailed doctors. After the war, it is true, he gave us
                  »<rs type="work" ref="#42883">Casanova’s Homecoming</rs>,« a pseudo-historical
               novel in which he reveals himself at the very acme of his creative talent and which
               constitutes one of his rare excursions outside of <rs type="place" ref="#50"
                  >Vienna</rs>.</p>
            <p>One cannot even attempt to condense so prolific an author and so genuine a
               personality as <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> into the framework of an
               article. In contemporary literature <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur
                  Schnitzler</rs> is considered one of the great trio of which <rs type="person"
                  ref="#11617">Gerhardt Hauptmann</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="#12176">Thomas
                  Mann</rs> are the other members. This despite the subject-matter of his works,
               which, as already mentioned, deal with rather superficial joys of life. For the
               critical reader, however, there are always two stories in any <rs type="person"
                  ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> book: One that plays in the foreground and is of
               apparently only local interest and skin-deep significance: but in the background, if
               one cares to delve deeper into <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>’s
               stories, there is enacted the eternal human tragedy of man in search of love, in fear
               of death and in a fruitless struggle to liberate himself from the material and
               sensual world.</p>
            <p>It is on this second plane that <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs>
               reminds one of <rs type="person" ref="#4279">Anatole France</rs> – a skeptic to whom
               nothing human is foreign, an observer who finds the eternal problems in the everyday
               life of a harlot or a soldier just as tragic as the tribulations of a statesman or an
               artist.</p>
            <p>As <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> enters his seventieth year – a
               commanding figure who has managed to keep himself above all the petty political
               gibbering of Europe, whose creative output has always been marked by an artistocratic
               distinction that made it possible for him to say and discuss everything without ever
               becoming vulgar – he represents the genuine artist. There is nothing of the
               professional man of letters in him. No jealousies, no best-seller attitude to
               literature. He hates, and always has hated, the literary charlatan who strives for
               effect and hastens to catch the latest literary vogue or school, hoping by means of
               his ability to be up-to-date to squeeze through the narrow gate of immortality. <rs
                  type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>’s books may not live much longer than
               the first half of the twentieth century – but to us, his contemporaries, he is a
               vital, nay, inspiring personality and author.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
