<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../meta/asischema.xsd"
   xml:base="schnitzler-interviews" xml:id="I091">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="s">Arthur Schnitzler: »Das Zeitlose ist von kürzester Dauer.« Interviews, Meinungen, Proteste (1891–1931)</title>
            <title level="a" ref="#58426">David Ewen: Arthur Schnitzler.&#8239;An Interview and
               Appreciation, Januar 1932</title>
            <author ref="#11277">Ewen, David</author>
            <editor>
               <name>Müller, Martin Anton</name>
            </editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>ASI</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transkription und Kommentierung</resp>
               <name>Martin Anton Müller</name>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Martin Anton Müller</publisher>
            <idno type="asi" n="091"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listBibl>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="#11277">Ewen, David</author>
                     <title level="a" ref="#58426">Arthur Schnitzler. An Interview and
                        Appreciation</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j" ref="#58580">B’nai B’rith Magazine. National Jewish
                        Monthly</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="1932-01-01" n="1">Januar 1932</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="vol">46</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="nr">4</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">73–74</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en-US">Englisch</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="approved">
         <change who="MAM" when="2018-10-19">angelegt aus Julia Glunks Abschrift</change>
         <change who="MAM" when="2021-09-17">Index check</change>
         <change who="KH" when="2021-11-03">Durchsicht</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="text">
      <body>
         <div type="original" xml:lang="en-US">
            <head>An Interview and Appreciation</head>
            <head type="sub">By David Ewen</head>
            <head type="sub">Last Interview</head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">
                  <hi rend="capitals">
                     <hi rend="spaced_out">Arthur </hi>
                  </hi>
                  <rs type="person" ref="#2121">
                     <hi rend="capitals">
                        <hi rend="spaced_out">Schnitzler</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </rs>, great novelist and playwright of <rs type="place" ref="#41240"
                  >Austria</rs>, whose books are known and loved by cultured people all over the
                  world, died of a stroke at his home on <date>October 21</date>. One of the last
                  interviews for publication he granted before his death, if not the very last was
                  granted to David Ewen, Jewish journalist from <rs type="place" ref="#44053">New
                     York</rs>, who visited him in <rs type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs> last
                  summer. The fruits of that interview are presented herewith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">On the opposite page is a critical appreciation of the work of <rs
                     type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> by <rs type="person" ref="#57984"
                     >Isaac Goldberg</rs>, well-known critic and author of »<rs type="work"
                     ref="#57987">The Man Mencken</rs>,« »<rs type="work" ref="#57989">Havelock
                     Ellis</rs>,« »<rs type="work" ref="#57991">The Theatre of George Jean
                     Nathan</rs>,« and many other books of literary and artistic interest.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">
                  <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs> was buried in <rs
                     type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs> after a short and simple Jewish service, in
                  accordance with his instructions for a pauper’s funeral. The money thus saved was,
                  according to his direction, distributed among hospitals.</hi>
            </p>
            <head type="sub">
               <rs type="person" ref="#2121">
                  <hi rend="capitals">
                     <hi rend="spaced_out">Arthur Schnitzler</hi>
                  </hi>
               </rs>. </head>
            <p>In the modern literary world, few names stand out so significantly as that of <rs
                  type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs>. A novelist who brought wisdom, a
               tremendous breadth and scope, a <hi rend="spaced_out">psychological</hi> penetration
               within his pages; a short-story writer of exquisite subtlety and delicacy; a
               playwright who infused breaths of life into the nostrils of each of his characters –
                  <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs> was an artist to the tips of
               his fingers, an artist who was easily one of the outstanding men of genius of our
               time. Of course, no one can hope to prophesy which of our contemporary literary works
               will struggle their way into immortality; such prophecy has more than once proved to
               be dishearteningly inaccurate. Yet, if any of our modern literary achievements are
               destined to attain permanency, there is little doubt among any of our critics that at
               least a few of <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>’s <anchor
                  type="textConst" xml:id="T_I091-1"/>unforgettable<note type="textConst"
                  xml:id="T_I091-1h"><quote>unforgetable</quote></note> tales will be numbered
               among them. Perhaps it will be the wistful and tender sadness of <rs type="work"
                  ref="#29985">
                  <hi rend="italics">The Lonely Way</hi>
               </rs> one of the great plays of our age; perhaps it will be his remarkable
               psychological studies of men and women – <rs type="work" ref="#30486">
                  <hi rend="italics">Bertha Garlan</hi>
               </rs>, <rs type="work" ref="#29941">
                  <hi rend="italics">Fraulein Else</hi>
               </rs>, <rs type="work" ref="#30817">
                  <hi rend="italics">Therese</hi>
               </rs> – characters which are so vividly etched that they seem to be among us;
               perhaps, it will be his short stories – exquisite moods, each one of them. But
               certainly works such as these cannot pass into oblivion! They have the permanency of
               all great things – that permanency which defies time and customs, a permanency which
               makes these works as immortal as the art they have so enriched.</p>
            <p>Jews may well be proud of <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs> – and
               proud, not only because he was a man of genius (for that, certainly, is no novelty!)
               but also because he was one of those very rare souls who did not sell their
               birthright for a bowl of pottage. Born a Jew, <rs type="person" ref="#2121"
                  >Schnitzler</rs> – unlike so many other geniuses – lived as a Jew throughout his
               entire life. Very few indeed, are the great Jewish artists who have not immersed
               themselves so deeply in their art as to forget their race and heritage. <rs
                  type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs> not only did not forget his race,
               he was not only a Jew in heart and in soul throughout his career, but he also
               enlisted, time and again, his gifted pen for Jewish causes. When he felt the stings
               of anti-Semitism levelled against the Jew, he wrote <rs type="work" ref="#30203">
                  <hi rend="italics">Prof. Bernhardi</hi>
               </rs> – a supremely vitriolic play about anti-Semitism among physicians. In the <rs
                  type="work" ref="#29923">
                  <hi rend="italics">Open Road</hi>
               </rs>, he discussed the many problems facing the Jew with that clarity, wisdom, and
               penetration which we had long before begun to associate with his writings. And the
                  <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="K_I091-6"/>number of articles on Jewish
                  questions<note type="commentary" xml:id="K_I091-6h">solche Artikel hat er nicht
                  geschrieben und publiziert</note> which he produced is incalculable. Never was he
               too busy with his other literary achievements to forget or slight his race when it
               needed his help.</p>
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs> – who died in his sixty-ninth
               year – was the son of <rs type="person" ref="#12695">Johann Schnitzler</rs>, a
               world-famous laryngologist. It seemed, therefore, that <rs type="person" ref="#2121"
                  >Arthur</rs> was destined from his birth to be a physician – to carry the name of
               Schnitzler to still <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="K_I091-11"/>greater
                  heights<note type="commentary" xml:id="K_I091-11h">Entgegen den hier
                  angeschlagenen Tönen von <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> als
                  medizinischer Nachwuchshoffnung, war er ein eher desinteressierter und
                  durchschnittlicher Student.</note> in the medical field. As a youth <rs
                  type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur</rs> showed himself to be so adept in scientific
               studies that it seemed apparent that such a son would easily bring honor to the name
               he bore. He went through his medical studies with ease and rapidity. The professors
               at the university were extolling his name. He was destined, they prophesied, for a
               great medical career.</p>
            <p>It was at the university that <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs>
               first was <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="K_I091-4"/>vividly brought to realize
               that he was a Jew – and what such a responsibility meant. But permit <rs
                  type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs> to speak to you himself, just as
               he spoke to me when I visited him. »When I was a student at the university, here in
                  <rs type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs>, a few of the more charitable students
               banded themselves together into a sort of philanthropic society. Our mission was to
               give charity to needy students. Of course, we could not afford to give very much, but
               we knew that even a meager few shillings were better than nothing and might spell the
               difference, to many a student, between living and starvation. It was not very long
               before discrimination set in. When a student pleaded for financial help and if his
               name was unmistakably Jewish – he was immediately, and subtly, removed from all
               consideration. Quite naturally, such discrimination struck me forcibly, and I fought
               bitterly against this unfair treatment which Jewish students received. But it was a
               hopeless fight, as I soon enough realized, and before long I was forced to resign
               from the society. That incident made a profound impression upon me. It was my first
               realization that the Jew was confronted with problems uniquely his own – and that the
               problems of the Jew were likewise my own problems<note type="commentary"
                  xml:id="K_I091-4h">Bei dieser Passage handelt es sich um eine Variation von <ref
                     target="#I032_L_society" type="pointer"/>.</note>.«</p>
            <p><anchor type="commentary" xml:id="K_I091-45"/>When <rs type="person" ref="#2121"
                  >Schnitzler</rs> graduated from the university – and he graduated with the highest
               of honors! – he entered his <rs type="person" ref="#12695" subtype="implied"
                  >father</rs>’s clinic in order to receive his final medical education under the
               mature guidance of his father. He profited much from his father’s instructions, and
               before long he was prepared to set out himself on a medical career. For a few years
               he travelled through <rs type="place" ref="#151">Germany</rs>, <rs type="place"
                  ref="#254">England</rs>, and <rs type="place" ref="#166">France</rs> to study
               medical conditions in those countries, and also to lecture frequently<note
                  type="commentary" xml:id="K_I091-45h">Diese Angaben sind falsch (Vorlesungen) oder
                  maßlos übertrieben.</note>. It was not long before he came into his own, before he
               attained a fame and prestige which dangerously rivalled that of his father.
               Everywhere he was soon recognized as the foremost specialist of laryngology of his
               time – having succeeded, even, in writing a very learned paper on the <rs type="work"
                  ref="#36059">
                  <hi rend="italics">Nervous Diseases of the Voice</hi>
               </rs> – and as the fitting successor to his great <rs type="person" subtype="implied"
                  ref="#12695">father</rs>. Everyone was now comfortably assured that the young
               doctor was headed straight towards greatness. The future, it seemed now certain,
               belonged to him.</p>
            <p>But his contemporaries had reckoned without him. In his <anchor type="commentary"
                  xml:id="K_I091-16"/>fortieth year<note type="commentary" xml:id="K_I091-16h"><rs
                     type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> war knapp 31, als sein <rs
                     type="person" subtype="implied" ref="#12695">Vater</rs> starb und er in Folge
                  die berufliche Tätigkeit als Arzt einstellen konnte, wenngleich er einzelne
                  Patientinnen und Patienten noch jahrelang betreute.</note>, <rs type="person"
                  ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> (with triumph ringing in his ears, and fame and
               success at his right hand) suddenly did the mad thing. He announced that he was
               forever through with medicine and that he would definitely give himself up to
               literature. Who can hope to explain how such things happen? Something had been long
               hidden in <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>’s heart, and at last it was
               crying for life, for expression, for the sunlight. And <rs type="person" ref="#2121"
                  >Schnitzler</rs> heeded the call meekly and bravely. And so, in the face of his
               bewildered friends and relatives – some of whom thought he had gone mad, and others
               of whom were confident that this was only an ephemeral whim – <rs type="person"
                  ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> hid himself from society for a full year. And he wrote
               his first play, <rs type="work" ref="#29823">
                  <hi rend="italics">Das Maerchen</hi>
               </rs>. And then the great physician exchanged his laurels and became now the great
               literary figure. Who will doubt that he had exchanged wisely?</p>
            <p>»Many of my friends,« Dr. <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> told me, in
               speaking about this incident, »still feel that I am a finer doctor than a literary
               man, and really have greater confidence in my treatments than in my novels and
               plays.« Perhaps. Yet when we read those pathetic, beautiful tales about women, which
               he has fashioned for us with such a tender hand, we may regret the passing of the
               great physician but we hail the arrival of a still greater literary figure. Medicine
               has other celebrated laryngologists, but literature has only one <rs type="person"
                  ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs>.</p>
            <p><anchor type="commentary" xml:id="K_I091-8"/>As <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur
                  Schnitzler</rs> and I were ramblingly discussing matters of literary and religious
               interest, I had the enviable opportunity of studying the great man at close range. We
               were sitting on the comfortably soft couch in his charming study. The walls were
               covered with books. One of these bookcases, modestly covered by a velvet curtain,
               contained <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs>’s works in all
               translated languages. The one window of the room looked out upon a luxuriously
               fertile garden where, during the spring, summer, and early autumn Dr. <rs
                  type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> did all of his writing. It was rapidly
               becoming dusk, and the room – as we were talking – was becoming suffused with a
               serene, mellow darkness. <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> did not
               trouble putting on the light. He was buried in the softness of his couch –
                  talking.<note type="commentary" xml:id="K_I091-8h">Bei dieser Passage handelt es
                  sich um eine Variation von <ref target="#I011_L1_bookcase" type="pointer"
                  />.</note></p>
            <p>From so close a range I could clearly see that in spirit and in flesh <rs
                  type="person" ref="#2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs> was an old man. True, many
               another man at his age still feels energetic and full of life. Just recently, Sir <rs
                  type="person" ref="#5194">Georg Henschel</rs> – who is already eighty years old –
               came to <rs type="place" ref="#175">America</rs> from <rs type="place" ref="#254"
                  >England</rs> to guest-conduct the <rs type="org" ref="#29427">Boston Symphony
                  Orchestra</rs>. But a man is as old as he feels, and <rs type="person" ref="#2121"
                  >Arthur Schnitzler</rs> then felt aged, indeed! The deep wrinkles of his face, the
               grayness of his beard and hair, the heavy bags under his eyes, his stooped back, his
               heavy gait, and his tired look all testified that his nearly seventy years weighed
               heavily upon him.</p>
            <p>And yet, although <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> felt his age very
               keenly, the realization brought him no pain or regret. He looked upon his old age,
               and the coming of death, with a philosophical stoicism which was as refreshing as it
               was beautiful. »<anchor type="commentary" xml:id="K_I091-43"/>Younger men than I have
               been known to die<note type="commentary" xml:id="K_I091-43h">Zitat von <ref
                     target="#I011_L2_todie" type="pointer"/></note>,« he said to me softly and
               peacefully – and I could clearly see that the contemplation of death held no terror
               for him. »I have worked hard during my life, and when the time comes, I am ready to
               go. Of course, as long as life is spared me, there will be more and more work for me
               to do. I am at the very present moment at work upon three books and, should they be
               fated to reach completion, I shall begin work on other books. However, I am always
               ready to drop my pen because I know that I have worked wisely and well during a
               lifetime. My conscience, at least, is clear in that direction.«</p>
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> lived in the outskirts of <rs
                  type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs> – in a luxurious villa on <anchor
                  type="textConst" xml:id="T_I091-111"/>
               <rs type="place" ref="#150">Sternwartestrasse</rs>
               <note type="textConst" xml:id="T_I091-111h"
                  ><quote>Sternwarterstrasse</quote></note> – which peeps out upon the glorious
               nearby <rs type="place" ref="#50">Vienna</rs> woods. Here he used to stay the greater
               part of his time, working with an industry astonishing for a man so old and so
               famous. In the back of his home there extends a tremendous garden – a <rs
                  type="place" ref="#40876">Wiener-Wald</rs> in miniature – in which <rs
                  type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>, on pleasant days, did his literary
               work. Winter and unfavorable weather found him in his study, on the second floor of
               his home, almost always alone. For when <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>
               was deep in work upon a new book he never permitted anyone to disturb him during
               working hours. His food was served in his study, and not even his family was
               permitted to interrupt him for any reason.</p>
            <p>He was a very careful, slow literary worker. Although he invariably worked upon two
               or three books at one time, each book received the most minute and scrupulous
               attention. Every page of his was revised dozens of times, and when a book was at last
               completed it was put aside for six months or a year, after which it underwent another
               minute and careful revision. It took an overwhelming amount of effort, pain and work
               to create any part of a <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> story. That is
               why, perhaps, each of his works – even his earliest ones – are such cameos of
               artistic perfection.</p>
            <p>From where did <rs type="person" ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs> get his literary
               material? The slightest scene, the most minute episode was sufficient to inflame his
               vivid imagination into a mighty and uncontrollable conflagration. A nude girl,
               running through some wild growth on the outskirts of <rs type="place" ref="#50"
                  >Vienna</rs>, brought innumerable little questions to <rs type="person"
                  ref="#2121">Schnitzler</rs>’s alert mind. The answer to those questions was <rs
                  type="work" ref="#29941">
                  <hi rend="italics">Fraulein Else</hi>
               </rs>. Another out-of-the-way episode – a chance remark by an acquaintance at a cafe
               – made possible his <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="K_I091-455"/><rs type="work"
                  ref="#56596">
                  <hi rend="italics">None But the Brave</hi>
               </rs><note type="commentary" xml:id="K_I091-455h"><rs type="work" ref="#29853"
                     >Lieutenant Gustl</rs>, in der Übersetzung von <rs type="person" ref="#12785"
                     >Richard Leo Simon</rs>, erschienen <date>1926</date> im Verlag <rs type="org"
                     ref="#29648">Simon <c rendition="#kaufmannsund"/> Schuster</rs></note>. And so,
               any little happening was possible material for a complex novel. And his notebooks and
               files were overcrowded with such little incidents! Who can tell how these unimportant
               episodes would have been translated into classics under <rs type="person" ref="#2121"
                  >Schnitzler</rs>’s touch had life been granted him for a few more years?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biographical">
            <div1>
               <ref type="schnitzlerDiary" target="1930-08-15"/>
               <quote>Nm. <rs type="person" ref="#11277">David Ewe<unclear>n</unclear>
                  </rs>, junger Journalist <rs type="place" ref="#44053">New York</rs>, dem ich ein
                  Interview abgeschlagen; Gespräch.–</quote>
            </div1>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
